<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-US"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en-US" /><updated>2023-08-08T09:34:56-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Exoplanet Radio</title><subtitle> Have you ever wondered what lies beyond our solar system? Are there other planets like Earth out there? How do we find them and study them? What can they teach us about ourselves and our place in the universe?  If you are curious about these questions, then Exoplanet Radio is for you. We will explore the fascinating field of exoplanets, the planets that orbit other stars. We will learn about the history and methods of exoplanet discovery, the diversity and characteristics of exoplanets, the challenges and opportunities of exoplanet science, and the implications and prospects of exoplanet life.  Join us on this journey of wonder and discovery, as we venture into the unknown and uncover the secrets of the worlds beyond our solar system.</subtitle><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">A Giant Planet Found Orbiting a Small Star</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/giant-planet-around-small-star/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Giant Planet Found Orbiting a Small Star" /><published>2023-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/discoveries/giant-planet-around-small-star</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/giant-planet-around-small-star/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 8th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/015-giant-planet-small-star-final/015_GiantPlanetSmallStar_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/015-giant-planet-small-star-final/015_GiantPlanetSmallStar_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A massive, Jupiter-sized exoplanet has been discovered orbiting a small, low-mass star and this discovery is challenging theories on how planets form around their stars. The planet, called TOI-4860 b, is about the same size as Jupiter and orbits its star once every 1.5 Earth days, classifying it as a warm Jupiter. This is unusual because planets this large are not supposed to form around low-mass stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exoplanet orbits the red dwarf star TOI-4860. Located in the constellation of Corvus the crow some 261 light years away, TOI-4860 has a mass equivalent to just around a third of our Sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get this large, the team that discovered TOI-4860 b believes that the planet may have formed from a disk of material that was enriched in heavy elements. This enrichment could have helped the planet to grow to its current size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery of TOI-4860 b challenges our understanding of how planets form. The traditional model of planet formation says that planets form from disks of gas and dust that surround young stars. The amount of material in these disks is thought to be related to the mass of the star. So, a low-mass star would have a less massive disk, and therefore would not be able to form a planet as large as TOI-4860 b.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, astronomers believe that there may be another way for planets to form around low-mass stars. These planets may have formed from the merger of smaller planets. This would require a very specific set of circumstances, but it is possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TOI-4860 b was first spotted by NASA’s Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS), which hunts planets outside the solar system by looking for tiny drops in the brightness of light emitted by stars. Those dimmings are caused as an orbiting planet crosses between the host star and our telesocpes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery of TOI-4860 b is a reminder that we still have a lot to learn about how planets form. This discovery is just one more piece of the puzzle, and it will be exciting to see what else we learn in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding planets in locations we don’t expect and in regions that defy our current understanding is an important reason why astronomers scan the heavens in search of other worlds.  The universe is a vast and mysterious place and we have only just begun the quest for life in the universe and it all starts with these observations, performed by vigilant ground and space-based telescopes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="discoveries" /><summary type="html">Finding planets in locations we don’t expect and in regions that defy our current understanding is an important reason why astronomers scan the heavens in search of other worlds</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The First Exoplanets: The Discovery That Forever Changed Us</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/the-first-exoplanets/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The First Exoplanets: The Discovery That Forever Changed Us" /><published>2023-08-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/discoveries/the-first-exoplanets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/the-first-exoplanets/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 7th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/014-the-first-exoplanets-final/014_TheFirstExoplanets_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/014-the-first-exoplanets-final/014_TheFirstExoplanets_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our galaxy likely holds hundreds of billions of planets around other stars but when and how did we begin finding them?  What was the first exoplanet detected?  It turns out that the first discovery wasn’t one, but two planets in the same system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The steady drumbeat of exoplanet discovery began in 1992 when astronomers Aleksander Wolszczan and Dale Frail found two rocky planets orbiting a type of neutron star known as a pulsar, a rapidly spinning stellar corpse that pulses with millisecond bursts of searing radiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measuring slight changes in the timing of the pulses is what allowed scientists to reveal the two rocky planets in orbit around the pulsar.The planets were named Poltergeist and Phobetor, and they were about the size of Earth and Neptune, respectively. They orbited the pulsar at distances of about where the asteroid belt and Uranus is in our solar system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These first two planets found by humans on Earth are not habitable. They are too close to the pulsar, and are constantly bombarded by radiation. However, their discovery showed that planets can exist around other stars, and it opened up the possibility that there may be habitable planets out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding these planets around this spinning star essentially opened the floodgates, and hinted that there must be planets everywhere because if we can find planets around a neutron star, which is a very harsh environment, then the planet production process must be very robust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little bit later astronomers started looking for planets like ours and the first planet detected around a Sun-like star was in 1995, and turned out to be a hot Jupiter: a gas giant about half the mass of our own Jupiter in an extremely close, four-day orbit around its star. A year on this planet, in other words, lasts only four days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From these exciting beginnings, over 5,000 exoplanets have since been discovered and some of them are located in the habitable zone of their stars, which is the region around a star where liquid water could exist on the surface of a planet. Some of these planets are even Earth-sized, which makes them even more likely to be habitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery of exoplanets has opened up a new chapter in our understanding of the universe. We now know that planets are not just a unique feature of our own solar system, but are common throughout the galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are on the cusp of a new era of discovery, and the possibilities are endless. We are on a quest that will hopefully answer some of the most fundamental questions about our place in the universe, and that could also change the course of human history.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="discoveries" /><summary type="html">The observations of planets around other stars is very recent and it changed our view of humanity&apos;s place in the universe forever.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Finding Exoplanets</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/science/finding-exoplanets/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finding Exoplanets" /><published>2023-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/science/finding-exoplanets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/science/finding-exoplanets/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 4th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/013-finding-exoplanets/013_FindingExoplanets_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/013-finding-exoplanets/013_FindingExoplanets_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are a species of wonder. We have always looked up at the stars and wondered if we are alone in the universe. Are there other worlds out there, with other beings who look up at the stars and wonder about us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The search for exoplanets is our best chance of finding out. Exoplanets are planets that orbit stars other than the Sun. They are incredibly faint compared to their parent stars, but scientists have come up with some clever methods to find them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way is to measure the radial velocity of a star. This is the speed at which the star is moving towards or away from us. If a planet is orbiting the star, the gravitational pull of the planet will cause the star to wobble a little bit as it goes around. This wobble can be detected by looking at the movement of the spectrum of the star, measuring the star’s radial velocity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to find exoplanets is to look for transits. This is when a planet passes in front of its star, blocking out a little bit of the star’s light.  As the planet passes in front a tiny dip in brightness of the star is measured by very sensitive telescopes.  The amount of light blocked by the star gives us important information, such as the size of the planet, it’s distance from the star as well as the length of time to complete one orbit around the star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, it has become possible to use direct imaging to find exoplanets. This requires some of the best telescopes ever built and very sophisticated processing techniques, but optics, detectors and computer software have become so good that we can actually see the planets themselves. This is the most difficult method of finding exoplanets, but it’s the only way to see what they actually look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microlensing is also used by astronomers to look for the temporary brightening of a star caused by the gravitational lensing of a passing planet.  As a relatively dark planet passes in front of a star, its gravitational field causes the star to brighten as the light passes by. This brightening is very small, but it can be detected with sensitive telescopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few other methods that scientists use to find exoplanets, but these are the most common. As technology improves, we’re likely to discover more and more exoplanets using a variety of methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, scientists have discovered over 5,000 exoplanets. And they’re finding more all the time. We’re learning that there are all sorts of exoplanets out there, from gas giants to rocky worlds that could potentially support life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The search for exoplanets is one of the most exciting and inspiring quests in human history. And who knows what we might discover in the years to come? We might find Earth-like planets that could potentially support life. We might even find evidence of extraterrestrial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The search for exoplanets is a search for our place in the universe. It’s a search for our destiny.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html">How do astronomers find exoplanets? This episode explores the various ways planets around other stars reveal themselves.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">WASP-39b: A Hot, Jupiter-sized World</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/wasp39b-hot-jupiter/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WASP-39b: A Hot, Jupiter-sized World" /><published>2023-08-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/wasp39b-hot-jupiter</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/wasp39b-hot-jupiter/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 3rd, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/wasp-39b-final/WASP-39b_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/wasp-39b-final/WASP-39b_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we are going to visit WASP-39 b a gas giant planet that orbits a Sun-like star 700 light-years away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WASP-39 b is a hot and puffy planet with a mass roughly one-quarter that of Jupiter and a diameter 1.3 times greater than Jupiter. Its extreme puffiness is related in part to its high temperature of about 1,600 degrees Fahrenheit or 900 degrees Celsius. Unlike the cooler, more compact gas giants in our solar system, WASP-39 b orbits very close to its star – only about one-eighth the distance between the Sun and Mercury – completing one circuit in just over four Earth-days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it is so close to its host star, it is likely to be tidally locked, which means one side of the planet faces the star at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WASP-39 b was discovered in 2011 based on ground-based detections of the subtle, periodic dimming of light from its host star as the planet transits, or passes in front of the star. Since then, it has been studied by various telescopes, including NASA’s Hubble and Spitzer space telescopes, which revealed the presence of water vapor, sodium, and potassium in the planet’s atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the most exciting discovery came in July 2022, when WASP-39 b became the first exoplanet to be studied by NASA’s James Webb Space Telescope. The Webb Space Telescope captured the first clear evidence for carbon dioxide in the atmosphere of a planet outside the solar system. This observation provides important insights into the composition and formation of the planet. In November 2022, five science papers reported on WASP-39 b discoveries made using JWST. Those included the first observation of sulfur dioxide and photochemistry (chemical changes influenced by starlight) in an exoplanet atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WASP-39 b is a fascinating example of how diverse and complex exoplanets can be. By studying its atmosphere with Webb, we can learn more about how this planet formed and evolved, and how it compares to other gas giants in our galaxy. WASP-39 b is also a promising target for future observations with Webb, which may be able to detect and measure carbon dioxide in the thinner atmospheres of smaller rocky planets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="exoplanets" /><summary type="html">WASP-39 b is a fascinating example of how diverse and complex exoplanets can be.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">TRAPPIST-1: A System Full of Hope</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/trappist1-a-system-full-of-hope/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TRAPPIST-1: A System Full of Hope" /><published>2023-08-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/trappist1-a-system-full-of-hope</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/trappist1-a-system-full-of-hope/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 2nd, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/asystem-full-of-hope-final/ASystemFullOfHope_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/asystem-full-of-hope-final/ASystemFullOfHope_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from our own solar system, one of the most studied stellar systems lies about 40 light-years away in the direction of the constellation Aquarius. Using ground and space based telescopes like Spitzer, Kepler, Hubble, and, now, the James Webb Space Telescope, astronomers are looking hard at the seven rocky exoplanets orbiting the TRAPPIST-1 star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TRAPPIST-1 system, named after the Transiting Planets and Planetesimals Small Telescope (TRAPPIST) in Chile, is currently the darling of both the astronomical community and the science-interested public. Discovered in 2016 by a team of astronomers in Belgium, this captivating system captured the attention of many because of its uncanny resemblance to our own solar system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TRAPPIST-1 system features a host star dramatically cooler and smaller than our Sun, classified as an ultra-cool dwarf. Its surrounding cohort consists of seven known planets. The planets are all named after letters of the alphabet, starting with b, the innermost planet, and ending with h, the outermost planet. The planets are so close together that they could all fit inside the orbit of Mercury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, NASA announced the discovery that this system had the most Earth-sized planets found in the habitable zone of a single star. This system of seven rocky worlds–all of them with the potential for water on their surface – is an exciting discovery in the search for life on other worlds. There is the possibility that future study of this unique planetary system could reveal conditions suitable for life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit later, a closer study of the seven planets suggested that some could harbor far more water than the oceans of Earth, in the form of atmospheric water vapor for the planets closest to their star, liquid water for others, and ice for those farthest away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The form that water would take on TRAPPIST-1 planets would depend on the amount of heat they receive from their star, which is a mere 9 percent as massive as our Sun. Planets closest to the star are more likely to host water in the form of atmospheric vapor, while those farther away may have water frozen on their surfaces as ice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronomers say we now know more about the TRAPPIST-1 system of planets than any other planetary system apart from our own.  The excitement and hope that we may find life here is growing with every new observation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While data from Hubble and Webb Space Telescopes have yet to confirm the existence of any atmospheres on any of these worlds, we have only just begun looking and hope abides with each new glance at this incredible system.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="exoplanets" /><summary type="html">While data from Hubble and Webb Space Telescopes have yet to confirm the existence of any atmospheres on any of these worlds, we have only just begun looking and hope abides with each new glance at this incredible system</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exoplanet Detected in Another Galaxy?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/exoplanet-detected-another-galaxy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exoplanet Detected in Another Galaxy?" /><published>2023-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/discoveries/exoplanet-detected-another-galaxy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/exoplanet-detected-another-galaxy/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 1st, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/exoplanet-another-galaxy-final/ExoplanetAnotherGalaxy_final.wav&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/exoplanet-another-galaxy-final/ExoplanetAnotherGalaxy_final.wav&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronomers have found evidence of a possible planet outside of our Milky Way galaxy. If confirmed, this is the first time that a planet has been detected in another galaxy. It is located in the spiral galaxy Messier 51, also called the Whirlpool Galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exoplanets are defined as planets outside of our Solar System. Until now, astronomers have found all other known exoplanets and exoplanet candidates in the Milky Way galaxy, almost all of them less than about 3,000 light-years from Earth. An exoplanet in M51 would be about 28 million light-years away, meaning it would be thousands of times farther away than those in the Milky Way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These observations were made using NASA’s Chandra X-Ray Space Telescope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronomers estimate the planet is about the size of Saturn and orbits a neutron star or black hole at about twice the distance of Saturn from the Sun. The planet was discovered when dips in the brightness of X-rays were observed from the binary system M51-ULS-1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is fascinating because it’s the first time X-rays have been used to detect exoplanet transits and offers exciting possibilities for detecting these worlds that are outside of our galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The researchers are not totally sure if the dimming seen here was caused by a planet, it could have been a passing cloud of gas and dust. However, they believe that the dimming is more likely caused by a planet because the characteristics of the event are not consistent with the passage of a cloud of gas and dust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the region producing bright X-rays is so small, a planet passing in front of it could block most or all of the X-rays, making x-ray transits easier to spot because the X-rays can completely disappear, they would simply “blink out” as the planet passes by. This allows exoplanets to be detected at much greater distances than current optical light transits, which must be able to detect tiny decreases in light because the nearby planets only block a tiny fraction of the star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the dimming was caused by a planet, it would be the first planet ever discovered outside of the Milky Way galaxy. However, more data is needed to confirm the discovery. Because of the calculated orbit of the object, we will need to wait about 70 years for it to cross in front of its binary partner again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This possible planet is exciting because it opens up a new way to search for exoplanets. In the past, astronomers have only been able to find exoplanets in our own galaxy. However, by looking for X-ray transits in other galaxies, astronomers can now search for exoplanets much farther away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The researchers are hopeful that they will be able to find more exoplanet candidates in other galaxies. They are also planning to search for X-ray transits in Milky Way X-ray sources to discover new nearby planets in unusual environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This discovery is a major step forward in the search for exoplanets. It shows that there are likely many planets out there in other galaxies, and it opens up a new way to find them&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="discoveries" /><summary type="html">Astronomers have found evidence of a possible planet outside of our Milky Way galaxy</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The First Exoplanet of JWST</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/the-first-exoplanet-of-jwst/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The First Exoplanet of JWST" /><published>2023-07-31T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-31T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/discoveries/the-first-exoplanet-of-jwst</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/the-first-exoplanet-of-jwst/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for July 31st, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/the-first-exoplanet-of-jwst-final/TheFirstExoplanetOfJWST_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/the-first-exoplanet-of-jwst-final/TheFirstExoplanetOfJWST_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have long wondered if we are alone in the cosmos. If there are other worlds like ours, where life might flourish. Now, a new eye in the sky has given us a glimpse of one such world. The James Webb Space Telescope has detected its first exoplanet. Its name is LHS 475b, and astronomers believe it is remarkably similar to our own home planet. It is roughly the same size as Earth, only slightly smaller by a mere 1%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did JWST find this distant world?  As LHS 475b orbits its star, it sometimes passes in front of it, blocking some of its light. By analyzing the spectrum of that light, and measuring the decrease in brightness of the star as the planet moves in front, we can see the size and infer the density of the planet, and even infer something about its atmosphere if it has one - astronomers aren’t sure yet about that. This is the first exoplanet confirmed by this massive space telescope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what kind of world is LHS 475b? Is it a place where life could exist? We do not know for sure yet, but we can make some educated guesses. All we know right now are its size, distance from its star, its density and some details of its spectrum, but we can glean a few things from this small amount of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of its size, we know that it is a rocky world, not a gas giant. We know that it is very close to its star, much closer than Mercury is to our Sun. This means that it is very hot, perhaps too hot for liquid water to exist on its surface. If it has an atmosphere, the spectrum tells us it is unlikely to be rich in methane, like Titan’s. It may be more like Venus, with a thick blanket of carbon dioxide and clouds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LHS 475b orbits a red dwarf star, one of the most common types of stars in the galaxy. It is located 41 light years away from us, in the southern constellation of Octans. It is a faint star and much cooler than our Sun. But even so, it provides enough energy for its planet to shine in the infrared spectrum. And that is how the Webb Space Telescope saw it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just the beginning of our exploration of LHS 475b. We hope to learn more about its atmosphere, its climate, and its potential for life. We hope to find out if it is truly an Earth-like world, or if it is something else entirely. We hope to answer one of the oldest questions of humanity: are we alone? Or are there others out there, waiting for us to discover them?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="discoveries" /><summary type="html">This is the First Exoplanet Confirmed by JWST</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Exoplanet That Shouldn’t Exist</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/an-exoplanet-that-shouldnt-exist/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Exoplanet That Shouldn’t Exist" /><published>2023-07-28T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/an-exoplanet-that-shouldnt-exist</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/an-exoplanet-that-shouldnt-exist/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for July 28th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/the-exoplanet-that-shouldnt-exist-final/TheExoplanetThatShouldntExist_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/the-exoplanet-that-shouldnt-exist-final/TheExoplanetThatShouldntExist_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronomers have found a planet around a red giant star that should have been destroyed, yet it still exists, leaving astronomers to wonder why the planet is still there.  So what’s the puzzle?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, stars change as they age. Once a star has used up all its hydrogen fuel in the core, it begins to shrink, while the outer envelope expands as the star cools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When our Sun enters this stage in about 5 billion years, it will grow so large that it will engulf Mercury, Venus, and possibly Earth.  The Sun will become a Red Giant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The planet in question is 8 Ursa Minoris b and was discovered in 2015 by Korean astronomers using the “Doppler wobble” technique, which measures the gravitational pull of the planet on the star.  It is a red giant star 530 light years away in the constellation of Ursa Minor, the Little Bear. The star was named Baekdu and the planet was named Halla after the tallest mountains on the Korean peninsula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Halla is very close, twice as close as the Earth is to the Sun and orbits Baekdu once every 93 days and is about 1.3 times the mass of Jupiter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is going on here?  How can a planet survive the expansion of its star into a Red Giant?  How did it not get swallowed up being so close to it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronomers think that one of two things is going on. Either Baekdu was one star in a binary system and the merger of these two stars may have prevented the expansion of either star to a size large enough to engulf planet Halla. Or Halla may be a relatively newborn planet. The violent collision between the two stars may have produced a cloud of gas and dust from which the planet could have formed. In other words, the planet Halla may be a recently born so-called “second generation” planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nature always seems to have a way of surprising us, throwing us curve balls just when we think we know what’s going on. The discovery of a planet orbiting a helium-burning red giant star shows that exoplanets can appear in places where we didn’t think they could exist. When it comes to the 8 Ursa Minoris system, whether it’s due to the merger of two stars or the formation of a cloud of gas and dust from which the planet could have formed, or something else altogether, we can always count on nature to find a way to surprise us.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="exoplanets" /><summary type="html">How can a planet survive the expansion of its star into a Red Giant?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Proxima Centauri-b: The Closest Exoplanet to Earth</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/Proxima-Centauri-b/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Proxima Centauri-b: The Closest Exoplanet to Earth" /><published>2023-07-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/Proxima-Centauri-b</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/Proxima-Centauri-b/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for July 27th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/proxima-b/Proxima_b_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/proxima-b/Proxima_b_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- Courtesy of embedresponsively.com --&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;responsive-video-container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/841359263?dnt=true&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that the closest star to us has a planet around it that may be habitable? In 2016 astronomers discovered a planet around the red-dwarf star Proxima Centauri, which lies a short hop away astronomically speaking at 4 light years from Earth.  This planet, called Proxima Centauri b, is the closest planet to us from outside the solar system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proxima Centauri b is a very strange planet, it is only a tiny bit larger than Earth but it orbits its star in only 11.2 days - that is its year! It also orbits very close to the star, closer than Mercury orbits the Sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, even though it is so close to Proxima Centauri, that star is quite cool, which means the planet can orbit very closely and not be too hot.  In fact, the temperatures on Proxima b are such that any water that may be there would be liquid.  Which is a good thing if life were to evolve or if humans were to travel there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Red dwarf stars like Proxima Centauri are tiny compared to the Sun.  They are also the most common stars in the universe and live for trillions of years.  The long life of red dwarf stars provides a lot of time for life to form on any planets that may orbit them.  Because of this, some astronomers believe that red dwarf stars are the most likely place to find evidence of life elsewhere in the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, even though Proxima Centauri is our closest star, it is still four light years away.  It would take five million years to get there at typical airline speeds, and our current rocket technology is nowhere near ready to take us there, so for now, travel to Proxima Centauri b remains a dream.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="exoplanets" /><summary type="html">Proxima Centauri-b is an exoplanet right next door.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Many Exoplanets Are There?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/science/how-many-exoplanets/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Many Exoplanets Are There?" /><published>2023-07-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/science/how-many-exoplanets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/science/how-many-exoplanets/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for July 26th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/how-many-exoplanets-final/HowManyExoplanets_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/how-many-exoplanets-final/HowManyExoplanets_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We live on a pale blue dot, a tiny oasis of life in a vast and silent cosmos. But are we alone? Are there other worlds like ours, orbiting other stars, in other parts of our galaxy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is yes. There are billions of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the remarkable achievements of space telescopes like Kepler and TESS, we have discovered over 5,000 exoplanets – planets beyond our solar system – and thousands more await confirmation. These exoplanets come in all shapes and sizes, from gas giants larger than Jupiter to rocky worlds smaller than Earth. Some are scorching hot, some are freezing cold, and some are just right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we know which ones are just right? We look for the ones that orbit within the habitable zone of their stars – the range of distances where liquid water could exist on the surface. Liquid water is essential for life as we know it, and it is also a good indicator of a planet’s climate and geology.  They are the best candidates for finding life in our galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how many exoplanets are in the habitable zone? A recent study estimated that there could be 300 million habitable planets in the Milky Way. Some are just 30 light years from the Sun, which means that if we could travel at the speed of light, it would take us only 30 years to reach them. Of course, we can’t travel at that speed, but we can still observe them with our telescopes and learn more about their properties and potential for life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even 300 million is just a fraction of the total number of exoplanets in our galaxy. The study extrapolated that figure from a sample of stars observed by Kepler, which only covered only one section of the sky in the constellation of Cygnus the Swan.  Astronomers estimate based on Kepler observations, that every star in the Milky Way has at least one planet, and there are roughly 400 billion stars in the galaxy, which means there are hundreds of billions of planets in our home galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s an astonishing number. NASA estimates that there are at least 1,500 planets within just 50 light years of Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our galaxy is not alone. There are billions of other galaxies in the observable universe, each with billions of stars and planets of their own. The number of exoplanets in the cosmos is beyond our imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may never be able to visit them all, or even detect them all, but we can still marvel at their existence and wonder about their mysteries. We can still dream of finding another pale blue dot, another oasis of life, another civilization among the stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not alone. We are part of a cosmic family, a galaxy of worlds.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html">There are an average of 1.6 planets for every star in our galaxy</summary></entry></feed>