<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-US"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en-US" /><updated>2023-09-06T11:19:34-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Exoplanet Radio</title><subtitle> Have you ever wondered what lies beyond our solar system? Are there other planets like Earth out there? How do we find them and study them? What can they teach us about ourselves and our place in the universe?  If you are curious about these questions, then Exoplanet Radio is for you. We will explore the fascinating field of exoplanets, the planets that orbit other stars. We will learn about the history and methods of exoplanet discovery, the diversity and characteristics of exoplanets, the challenges and opportunities of exoplanet science, and the implications and prospects of exoplanet life.  Join us on this journey of wonder and discovery, as we venture into the unknown and uncover the secrets of the worlds beyond our solar system.</subtitle><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Astronomers Confirm Proxima Centauri b is Not a Transiting Exoplanet</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/proxima-centauri-b-not-transiting-exoplanet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Astronomers Confirm Proxima Centauri b is Not a Transiting Exoplanet" /><published>2023-09-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/discoveries/proxima-centauri-b-not-transiting-exoplanet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/proxima-centauri-b-not-transiting-exoplanet/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for September 6th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/031-proximab-no-transit-final/031_ProximabNoTransit_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/031-proximab-no-transit-final/031_ProximabNoTransit_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronomers have recently concluded an observation study of the closest exoplanet to Earth, Proxima Centauri b and found that the planet does not transit its star.  These observations settle a question that astronomers have been asking since the exoplanet’s discovery in 2016 using the radial velocity method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proxima Centauri b was discovered in August 2016 at the European Southern Observatory using a technique that watches the wobble of a star as the gravity from a planet in orbit around it, pulls the star to and fro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By watching the star in this way, astronomers can tell several things: how many planets are there (in this case there’s just one), how massive they are (proxima b has roughly the same mass as the Earth), and how fast they go around the star (proxima b takes 11 days to go around the star once).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is, astronomers also want a transit; they have never seen the planet pass between us and the star, leading astronomers to take a longer look at our nearest exoplanet neighbor.  Why is observing a transit such a big deal? When a planet passes in front of the star the light from that star can give us clues to the physical size of the planet, but more importantly, the James Webb Space Telescope can measure that light and tell us if there is an atmosphere present on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would be great news because not only is Proxima b our closest neighbor at a little over four light years, but it lies in the habitable zone of Proxima Centauri.  If proxima b had an atmosphere, and if it had water, then that water could be liquid and may sustain life as we understand it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So measuring a transit of Proxima Centauri b would give us very important data about the habitability of the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results of this recent study were disappointing however.  Looking at the system with data from the Spitzer Space telescope and instruments in operation on the ground at the European Southern Observatory, astronomers confirmed that the exoplanet, proxima centauri b does not transit the star, not even partially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly little has been learned about proxima b since its discovery. We don’t know how old it is,  whether it has an atmosphere, whether it is tidally locked, nor it’s precise size.  But because it is so close, it provides one of the best opportunities for learning about Earth-sized worlds around M-class dwarf stars.  This is important because there are a lot of systems like this and having one in our celestial backyard is an ideal laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronomers estimate that planets less than ten times the mass of Earth occur around M-class stars at a rate of about one per star. There is at least one rocky planet around every M dwarf, and there are more M-class stars than any other star out there.  The more we understand the Proxima Centauri system, the more we understand most of the exoplanets in our galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although a transit event would have been ideal, we can still learn a lot about Proxima b from other sources of information.  For example, the star Proxima Centauri is a flaring M-class dwarf, and it flares, a lot,  over 60 times a day.  This, coupled with the assumption that it is tidally locked to the star, and that it orbits very close, the chance of keeping an atmosphere is low and that would make habitability seem rather a rather remote possibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to keep looking, observing, measuring and analyzing the closest exoplanet system to the Earth.  We have in our celestial backyard a pristine laboratory for understanding the question of habitability on planets around other stars.  Most of the planets in our galaxy orbit M-class stars like this, and we are sitting right next door to one.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="discoveries" /><summary type="html">Proxima Centauri b does not pass between us and the star, astronomers confirm. This will make determining habitability harder.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/Proxima_b.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/Proxima_b.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Many Earth-Sized Worlds of TOI-700</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/many-worlds-toi-700/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Many Earth-Sized Worlds of TOI-700" /><published>2023-08-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/many-worlds-toi-700</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/many-worlds-toi-700/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 30th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/030-toi-700-final/030_TOI-700_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/030-toi-700-final/030_TOI-700_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most exciting exoplanetary systems discovered so far, and one we’ve talked about many times on Exoplanet Radio, is TRAPPIST-1, a system of of seven planets, all of them rocky and more or less Earth sized, and about three of them are in the habitable zone of the star.  But new observations from an amazing space telescope have just discovered a system that rivals TRAPPIST-1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Habitable zones and Earth-sized are words we hear a lot when we talk about other star systems because those words outline a hope that life might exist on their planets.  Life could possibly arise under many scenarios, and it’s entirely possible that life may well survive without it.  But based on our experience -here, on Earth -  life needs liquid water and if a planet might have it, then we are naturally interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TRAPPIST-1 has held our attention for a long time because it has so many rocky worlds orbiting a star that may allow some of them to have liquid water.  The promise of life is too great to ignore, so we turn our most powerful telescopes to this system whenever possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately, however, there’s been a new system on the block.  The Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite, or TESS, has brought us the discovery of a system that is every bit as interesting as TRAPPIST-1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Known as TOI 700, named because it is the 700th TESS Object of Interest cataloged by the mission, is a system that contains four worlds, all presumed to be rocky based on the parameters measured from the planets as they transit the star.  The four planets are imaginatively named b, c, d, and e with d and e being the most interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s the system like?  Well like TRAPPIST-1 all of these planets are very close to their star.  They all have orbits measured in days, the longest being TOI 700 e at 28 days.  The reason we’re seeing so many systems like this is that our transit measuring space telescopes don’t stare at the system long enough to get planets that take longer to go around their star.  Those types of planets are probably out there, but we haven’t seen them yet because we don’t look at them long enough.  TESS for example only looks at one region of the sky for 27 days before it moves onto another sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The star TOI 700 is a small, cool M dwarf star located around 100 light-years away in the southern constellation Dorado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The innermost planet, TOI 700 b, is about 90% Earth’s size and orbits the star every 10 days. TOI 700 c is over 2.5 times bigger than Earth and completes an orbit every 16 days. These planets are probably tidally locked, which means they spin only once per orbit such that one side always faces the star, just as one side of the Moon is always turned toward Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact all the planets are so close they may all be tidally locked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TOI 700 d and e reside in what astronomers are calling the optimistic habitable zone.  This is a term we’ve not mentioned before but refers to a range of distances from a star where liquid surface water could have existed at some point in a planet’s history.  Compare this to what we usually refer to as a habitable zone where liquid water could have existed over most of the planet’s lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TOI 700 d and e orbits in the optimistic habitable zone and are a little farther out, with TOI 700e, the most promising for habitability, orbiting once over 28 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like TRAPPIST-1 this system is full of promise Follow-up study of the TOI 700 system with space- and ground-based observatories is ongoing, and with each new observation, our anticipation of what we might learn about habitable exoplanets, and life elsewhere, grows.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="exoplanets" /><summary type="html">Move over TRAPPIST-1, there a new system that is just as exciting. TOI-700 is a system of four rocky, Earth-sized worlds and some might be habitable</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/toi700e_art.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/toi700e_art.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Meet TrES-2b: The Planet That Reflects Almost No Light</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/tres2b-planet-reflects-no-light/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meet TrES-2b: The Planet That Reflects Almost No Light" /><published>2023-08-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/tres2b-planet-reflects-no-light</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/tres2b-planet-reflects-no-light/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 29th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/029-tres-2b-planet-of-eternal-night-final/029_Tres-2b_PlanetOfEternalNight_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/029-tres-2b-planet-of-eternal-night-final/029_Tres-2b_PlanetOfEternalNight_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we are going to visit TrES-2b, a planet that is so dark that it reflects less than one percent of the sunlight falling on it. How can a planet be so black? What makes it glow like a burning ember? And what kind of weather does it have? Let’s find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This planet was discovered in August 2006 by the Trans-Atlantic Exoplanet Survey.  It became the very first planet observed by the Kepler Space Telescope with the designation Kepler-1b.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kepler-1b is a gas giant that is slightly larger than Jupiter and has one and a half times its mass, but orbits much closer to its star than Mercury does to our Sun. It takes only 2.5 days to complete one orbit, meaning that its year is very short. It also rotates synchronously with its star, meaning that one side always faces the star and the other side always faces away. This creates a huge temperature difference between the day and night sides, which can reach up to 1,500 degrees Celsius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The star that Kepler-1b orbits is located about 700 light-years away from Earth in the constellation of Draco. It is a yellow dwarf star that is slightly smaller and cooler than our Sun, but still very bright. In fact, you can see it with the naked eye from Earth if you know where to look. It is part of a binary system, meaning that it has another star orbiting around it at a distance of about 50 astronomical units. This is equivalent to the distance between the Sun and Pluto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, why is TrES-2b so dark? Astronomers are not entirely sure, but they have some theories. One possibility is that the planet has a thick atmosphere that contains molecules that absorb light very efficiently, such as titanium oxide or sodium. Another possibility is that the planet has a layer of clouds that are made of graphite or other carbon-based materials that reflect very little light. Either way, the result is that Kepler-1b appears almost black in visible light, making it one of the darkest objects in our galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Kepler-1b is not completely dark. Because it is so hot, it emits infrared radiation that can be detected by telescopes. In fact, it glows like a burning ember or the coils on an electric stove. This means that if you could see it in infrared light, it would look very different from how it looks in visible light. It would also have some color variations depending on the temperature and composition of its atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting feature of Kepler-1b is its weather. Because of the extreme temperature difference between its day and night sides, the planet has very strong winds that blow at over 7,000 km/h, creating a supersonic shock wave on its trailing hemisphere. This shock wave compresses and heats up the gas behind it, creating a hot spot on the night side of the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kepler-1b is one of the most mysterious and extreme exoplanets ever discovered.  It is a planet of eternal night.  Astronomers believe that with air as hot as lava, this world may be giving off an eerie red glow as you float in the burning atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="exoplanets" /><summary type="html">Here is a planet that is so dark that it reflects less than one percent of the sunlight falling on it. How can a planet be so black? What makes it glow like a burning ember? And what kind of weather does it have?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/TrES-2b_artist.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/TrES-2b_artist.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How Starshades Can Help Us Find New Worlds</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/science/starshades-find-exoplanets/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Starshades Can Help Us Find New Worlds" /><published>2023-08-28T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/science/starshades-find-exoplanets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/science/starshades-find-exoplanets/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 28th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/028-starshades-final/028_Starshades_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/028-starshades-final/028_Starshades_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the 5000 exoplanets discovered so far have been found using methods that don’t actually see the planet at all.  Brightness dimmings and star wobbles only get us so far.  They limit our ability to study them in detail and astronomers are working on gigantic starshades to resolve planets directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Direct imaging is a technique that can be used to take pictures of exoplanets. But this is a much more challenging task than indirect methods, because the light from the exoplanet is much fainter than the light from the star it orbits. However, direct imaging is the only way to obtain detailed information about the physical properties of exoplanets, such as their geography, shape, and atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to improve the sensitivity of direct imaging is to use a starshade. A starshade is a large, deployable structure that looks a lot like a gigantic flower that blocks out the light from a star, allowing a telescope to see the fainter light from an orbiting planet. Starshades are still in the development stage, but they have the potential to revolutionize the field of exoplanet research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does a starshade work? It works by creating a shadow in the space between the telescope and the star. The shadow is created by the starshade’s petals, which are arranged in a circular or hexagonal pattern. The shape of the petals is designed to reduce diffraction and minimize the amount of stray light that enters the shadow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The starshade is positioned in front of the telescope, and the telescope is pointed at the star. With the light from the star blocked, the reflected light from the planet is revealed and the telescope can then see the faint glow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several challenges associated with using starshades to find exoplanets. One challenge is the size of the starshade.  They are huge and they need to be large enough to block out the light from the star, but they also need to be light enough to be deployed in space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another challenge is the alignment of the starshade. It needs to be aligned very precisely with the telescope in order to create a sharp shadow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several ongoing projects to develop starshades. One project is the HabEx mission, which is a joint project between NASA and the European Space Agency. The HabEx mission would use a starshade to search for Earth-like planets around nearby stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another project is the Roman Starshade Rendezvous, which is a NASA mission that will attempt to directly image the habitable zones of nearby sun-like stars. They will attempt to determine whether Earth-like exoplanets exist in the HZs of the nearest sunlike stars and have biosignature gases in their atmospheres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The development of starshades is still in the early stages, but they have the potential to make major advances in our understanding of exoplanets. Starshades could help us to find new exoplanets, to study their atmospheres, and to search for signs of life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html">Most of the 5000 exoplanets discovered so far have been found using methods that don’t actually see the planet at all. Brightness dimmings and star wobbles only get us so far. They limit our ability to study them in detail and astronomers are working on gigantic starshades to resolve planets directly</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/StarshadeConcept.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/StarshadeConcept.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Nancy Grace Roman Space Telescope will Revolutionize our Understanding of Exoplanets</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/science/nancy-grace-roman-space-telescope-exoplanets/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Nancy Grace Roman Space Telescope will Revolutionize our Understanding of Exoplanets" /><published>2023-08-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/science/nancy-grace-roman-space-telescope-exoplanets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/science/nancy-grace-roman-space-telescope-exoplanets/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 25th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/027-roman-space-telescope-final/027_RomanSpaceTelescope_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/027-roman-space-telescope-final/027_RomanSpaceTelescope_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We live in a golden age of exoplanet discovery.  Not only are we searching for and finding new worlds around other stars all the time, but as our technology improves we are learning more about these exotic places and inexorably bearing down on the all important answer to the question of whether life elsewhere exists in our galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next big milestone in our study of exoplanets is  a telescope that can see beyond the limits of our eyes, beyond the boundaries of our solar system, beyond the frontiers of our knowledge. A telescope that can reveal the secrets of the stars and the mysteries of the planets. A telescope that can take us closer to finding another home in the cosmos. That telescope is the Nancy Grace Roman Space Telescope, a NASA observatory that is scheduled to launch in May 2027 and explore a wide range of astronomical phenomena, including exoplanets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observing planets around other stars is a difficult business, one that pushes the boundaries of our technology.   Studying dim, small and elusive worlds to discover their potential for habitability requires novel techniques and state of the art telescopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get the observations we need, the Roman Space Telescope will employ three techniques to study exoplanets: microlensing, direct imaging, and transit method. Each of these methods has its own advantages and limitations, and together they will provide a comprehensive view of the formation, evolution, and physical properties of planetary systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microlensing looks for a tiny flash of light from a background star as a planet moves between us  and the background star.  This flash is a signal that betrays the existence of a relatively small, dark world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transit method looks for tiny dips in brightness as a planet blocks out part of the star’s light.  These dimmings tell us a lot about the size of the planet, its orbit around the star and the length of its year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Direct imaging is the holy grail, the new thing humanity can do. Planets are billions of times dimmer than their host stars, they are so bright we can’t see the planet directly unless we block it.  To solve this problem, astronomers and engineers have been working on ways to take a direct look at small, Earth-sized worlds that lie hidden behind the glare of their star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Roman Space Telescope will demonstrate direct imaging technology that has never been flown aboard a space-based observatory before. Using this technology, Roman will help pave the way for future missions to image Earth-like planets around nearby stars and measure their spectra to search for signs of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By using these complementary approaches, Roman will provide the most complete picture yet of the diversity and complexity of exoplanets. Roman will also take us another step closer to discovering another “pale blue dot” — a habitable, Earth-like planet orbiting a nearby star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not just science fiction. This is science fact. This is what Roman will do for us. This is why Roman matters. This is how Roman will help advance knowledge about exoplanets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html">The next big milestone in our study of exoplanets is a telescope that can see beyond the limits of our eyes, beyond the boundaries of our solar system, beyond the frontiers of our knowledge. A telescope that can reveal the secrets of the stars and the mysteries of the planets. A telescope that can take us closer to finding another home in the cosmos</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/RomanSpaceTelescope.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/RomanSpaceTelescope.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Is TRAPPIST-1 c Habitable? New Webb Telescope Observations Suggest Not</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/jwst-trappist1c-no-thick-atmosphere/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is TRAPPIST-1 c Habitable? New Webb Telescope Observations Suggest Not" /><published>2023-08-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/discoveries/jwst-trappist1c-no-thick-atmosphere</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/jwst-trappist1c-no-thick-atmosphere/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 24th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/026-jwsttrappist-1c-final_202308/026_JWSTTRAPPIST-1c_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/026-jwsttrappist-1c-final_202308/026_JWSTTRAPPIST-1c_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A team of astronomers used the James Webb Space Telescope to study the exoplanet TRAPPIST-1 c, which is one of seven rocky planets orbiting an ultracool red dwarf star 40 light-years from Earth. The team found that the planet’s atmosphere, if it exists at all, is extremely thin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TRAPPIST-1 c is about the same size as Venus and receives a similar amount of radiation from its host star as Venus gets from the Sun. This led scientists to believe that the planet might have a thick carbon dioxide atmosphere like Venus. However, the Webb observations suggest that this is not the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team used the Mid-Infrared Instrument on the Webb space telescope to observe TRAPPIST-1 c as it moved behind its star.   Webb can detect the heat that comes from the planet when it passes behind the star, which is called a secondary eclipse. By comparing the brightness of the star when the planet was behind it to the brightness when the planet was in front of it, the team was able to measure the amount of heat energy coming from the planet’s dayside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount of heat energy emitted by a planet is directly related to its temperature, which in turn is influenced by its atmosphere. Carbon dioxide gas preferentially absorbs heat energy at the wavelengths that MIRI is sensitive to, so if TRAPPIST-1 c had a thick carbon dioxide atmosphere, the team would have seen a smaller decrease in brightness when the planet moved behind its star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the team did not see a significant decrease in brightness, which suggests that the planet’s atmosphere, if it exists at all, is very thin. The team estimates that the atmosphere of TRAPPIST-1 c is at least 100 times thinner than Earth’s atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lack of a thick atmosphere around TRAPPIST-1 c suggests that the planet may have formed with relatively little water. This is because water vapor is a major component of thick atmospheres, and if TRAPPIST-1 c had a lot of water vapor, it would have been easier for the planet to retain a thick atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The absence of a thick atmosphere also makes it less likely that TRAPPIST-1 c is habitable. Habitable planets are thought to need thick atmospheres to protect them from harmful radiation and to help regulate their temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All is not lost however with regard to the TRAPPIST-1 system.  This planet is after all, very close to the star and just outside the region where liquid water could exist on the surface.  The observations of TRAPPIST-1c support the idea that planets close to their star have trouble holding on to an atmosphere, but that may not be the case with planets further out and actually inside the habitable zone, notably the planets TRAPPIST-1 e,f and g.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The findings of this study are a significant step forward in our understanding of exoplanets. The Webb space telescope is still in its early stages of operation, and scientists are excited to see what other discoveries it will make in the years to come.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="discoveries" /><summary type="html">TRAPPIST-1 c may not have a thick atmosphere, or any atmosphere at all, but all is not lost on the habitability of the TRAPPIST-1 system</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/TRAPPIST-1c_Artist.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/TRAPPIST-1c_Artist.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Trillions of Worlds Without Stars</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/trillions-of-worlds-without-stars/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trillions of Worlds Without Stars" /><published>2023-08-23T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/discoveries/trillions-of-worlds-without-stars</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/trillions-of-worlds-without-stars/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 23rd, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/025-trillions-of-worlds-without-stars-final/025_TrillionsOfWorldsWithoutStars_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/025-trillions-of-worlds-without-stars-final/025_TrillionsOfWorldsWithoutStars_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronomers estimate that there are more free roaming planets in our galaxy than there are planets in orbit around stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, rogue exoplanets - planets with no star whatsoever - far outnumber all other planets in our galaxy, by 20 times.  Trillions of worlds wandering alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronomers have reached this conclusion based on the results of a nine year survey that looked at special events that occur when an object such as a star or planet comes into near-perfect alignment with an unrelated background star from our vantage point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because anything with mass warps the fabric of space-time, light from the distant star bends around the nearer object as it passes close by. The nearer object acts as a natural lens, creating a brief spike in the brightness of the background star’s light that gives astronomers clues about the foreground object that they can’t see any other way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Known as microlensing events, they are our primary method of observing free-floating planets in our galaxy.  Since they do not shine light on their own, planets are usually observed by looking at their reflected light of the star.  Even then, seeing exoplanets is hard.  We have to block out the light from the star to see anything at all, something we’ve only just been able to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another big way of seeing exoplanets is to infer their existence with dips in brightness from transits, or gravitational wobbling as stars were pulled around by their planets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this means that seeing exoplanets is a difficult business, but it’s not impossible.  Microlensing is one more technique in the arsenal of astronomers to detect these small, dark worlds.  We are using gravity to discover objects we would have no hope of seeing directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nine year survey recently completed by astronomers found one Earth-sized rogue planet and the second discovery of its kind.  The study also analyzed the survey data and concluded that rogue planets are more abundant than all other planets in our galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Astronomers reason that rogue exoplanets tend to be smaller, Earth-sized or less.  Since they are small, they are more weakly tethered to their host star, and could be pulled away easier during gravitational encounters with other objects in the galaxy.   Another reason lies with the fact that planet building is a chaotic business that could easily see Earth-sized bodies thrown out of a nascent planetary system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding exoplanets in microlensing events is extraordinarily rare, the stars literally have to line up perfectly for us to be able to see them.  Each microlensing event is a one-time occurrence, meaning astronomers can’t go back and repeat the observations once they’re over.  So the best thing to do is look at large areas of the sky at once for a long time, to try and detect these small blips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to test these results, astronomers are looking forward to the launch of the wide-field Nancy Grace Roman Space Telescope in May 2027.  Roman will be sensitive to even lower-mass rogue planets since it will observe from space, and it is estimated that it will find 400 rogue planets when it begins its survey of the heavens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with ground-based telescopes these observations will help scientists measure the masses of rogue planets much more accurately than ever before, deepening our understanding of these dark nomads that grace our galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="discoveries" /><summary type="html">Astronomers estimate that there are more free roaming planets in our galaxy than there are planets in orbit around stars</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/IcyRogueWorld.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/IcyRogueWorld.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How Common are Habitable Exoplanets?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/science/how-common-habitable-exoplanets/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Common are Habitable Exoplanets?" /><published>2023-08-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/science/how-common-habitable-exoplanets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/science/how-common-habitable-exoplanets/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 22nd, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/024-how-common-exoplanets-final/024_HowCommonExoplanets_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/024-how-common-exoplanets-final/024_HowCommonExoplanets_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the big questions we are trying to answer in exoplanet astronomy is: Just how common are habitable planets?  We already know that exoplanets themselves are extremely common: Astronomers tell us there are on average 1.6 planets for every star in our galaxy, so there are more planets than stars out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That by itself is pretty amazing, but what we really want to know is, where’s the life?  How common are planets that could potentially support life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer so far has eluded us, and the news reports and studies coming out are a bit contradictory.  For example, as this recording is made, in July, 2023, over the course of just three days two studies were announced.  One is titled:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Potentially Habitable Worlds are 100x times more common than We Thought” and a few day later: “Latest James Webb Space Telescope images hint that habitable planets are not common”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From these headlines, it’s pretty clear that we are still sorting out how common habitability is, which is understandable because we’ve only just started studying exoplanets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are astronomers looking for and how are they doing it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronomers are using every tool at their disposal to understand the habitability question of exoplanets.  Space Telescopes like Webb, Spitzer, Hubble, Kepler, TESS, and many others are setting their sites on finding and confirming exoplanets, arranging them by size and whether they exist in a habitable zone of their host star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ground-based telescopes are measuring the wobble in the spectra of stars to determine planet masses and orbital periods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the real breakthrough will be measuring exoplanets directly and observing their disks when possible.  Right now, only the James Webb Space Telescope stands equipped to make those measurements.  Its mirror has the resolution necessary to see the exoplanets but more importantly it has a spectrograph that can measure the starlight as it travels through any atmosphere that might exist and give hints as to what it’s made of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main things JWST can show us with respect to the habitability of a given exoplanet are: whether it has an atmosphere, if it has one, what are some of the major chemical components of that atmosphere, including water, and crucially: are there any biosignatures in the atmosphere?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biosignatures are those elements that are produced by life and accumulate in an atmosphere to detectable levels.  What are they?  Astronomers are taking the approach that since we know what compounds life on Earth produces, let’s look for those first.  What might the spectrum of Earth look like if it was transplanted to another, slightly different, Earth-like planet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things like an oxygen-rich atmosphere, certain methane compounds, ammonia and carbon monoxide are good things to see for a start.  The trick for JWST will be getting enough orbits to make good measurements.  Since time is precious on JWST, this means that looking for planets that go around their stars quickly, and a primary candidate is the fascinating system of TRAPPIST-1.  Home to several worlds that could harbor life, are close to their star and orbit quicky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let’s not be too hard on astronomers this early in the search.  Right now our observations are preliminary and rough.  As they improve, our understanding of whether habitable planets are common or not will only get better.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html">How common are habitable exoplanets? Where&apos;s the life? Astronomers are using all tools at their disposal to answer this question.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/WaterMoonAroundGasGiant.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/WaterMoonAroundGasGiant.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">KELT-9b: The Hottest Known Exoplanet</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/kelt9b-hottest-known-exoplanet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="KELT-9b: The Hottest Known Exoplanet" /><published>2023-08-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/kelt9b-hottest-known-exoplanet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/kelt9b-hottest-known-exoplanet/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 18th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/023-kelt-9b-hottest-exoplanet-final/023_KELT-9bHottestExoplanet_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/023-kelt-9b-hottest-exoplanet-final/023_KELT-9bHottestExoplanet_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this episode, we are going to take a look at an extreme planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kelt-9b is a gas giant planet that orbits a star 670 light-years from Earth. It is so close to its star that its dayside temperature is 7,800 degrees Fahrenheit (4,300 degrees Celsius), hotter than some stars. This heat is so intense that it rips apart the molecules in the planet’s atmosphere, including hydrogen gas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But its star, called KELT-9, is even hotter – a blue A-type star that is likely unraveling the planet through evaporation.  The KELT-9 is only 300 million years old, which is young for a star. It is more than twice as large, and nearly twice as hot, as our sun. Given that the planet’s atmosphere is constantly blasted with high levels of ultraviolet radiation, the planet may even be shedding a tail of evaporated planetary material like a comet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery of Kelt-9b was announced in 2017 by a team of astronomers using the Kilodegree Extremely Little Telescope (KELT) system. The KELT system is a network of two robotic telescopes that are used to search for exoplanets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kelt-9b is a very massive planet, with a mass that is about three times that of Jupiter. The heat is caused by the proximity of the planet to its star. Kelt-9b orbits its star in just 36 hours, which means that it is constantly bathed in the star’s heat.  The planet is also unusual in that it orbits perpendicular to the spin axis of the star. That would be analogous to the planet orbiting perpendicular to the plane of our solar system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extreme heat of Kelt-9b has a profound effect on its atmosphere. The heat is so intense that it rips apart the molecules in the atmosphere, including hydrogen gas. This process is called photodissociation. The broken-up atoms then flow to the nightside of the planet, where it is cooler. On the nightside, the atoms can recombine to form molecules again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With each orbit, KELT-9 b twice experiences the full range of stellar temperatures, producing what amounts to a peculiar seasonal sequence. The planet experiences “summer” when it swings over each hot pole and “winter” when it passes over the star’s cooler midsection. So KELT-9 b experiences two summers and two winters every orbit, with each season about nine hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process is happening constantly on Kelt-9b, which means that the planet’s atmosphere is constantly being recycled. This makes it very difficult for any life to exist on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of Kelt-9b and other hot Jupiters is helping astronomers to better understand the formation and evolution of exoplanets. It is also helping them to learn more about the limits of habitability in the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to being the hottest exoplanet known, Kelt-9b is also one of the brightest. This makes it a valuable target for further study. Astronomers are using telescopes like the James Webb Space Telescope to learn more about the atmosphere of Kelt-9b.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of Kelt-9b is just one example of the exciting discoveries that are being made in the field of exoplanet research. As astronomers continue to study these distant worlds, they are learning more about the diversity of planets that exist beyond our solar system. This knowledge is helping us to better understand our own place in the universe.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="exoplanets" /><summary type="html">Kelt-9b is a gas giant planet that orbits a star 670 light-years from Earth. It is so close to its star that its dayside temperature is 7,800 degrees Fahrenheit (4,300 degrees Celsius), hotter than some stars. This heat is so intense that it rips apart the molecules in the planet&apos;s atmosphere, including hydrogen gas</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/KELT-9b.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/KELT-9b.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">HAT-P-67 b: The Largest Exoplanet Known</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/largest-known-exoplanet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="HAT-P-67 b: The Largest Exoplanet Known" /><published>2023-08-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/largest-known-exoplanet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/largest-known-exoplanet/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 17th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/022-the-largest-exopplanet-final/022_TheLargestExopplanet_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/022-the-largest-exopplanet-final/022_TheLargestExopplanet_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exoplanet astronomy is a new science, astronomers have only confirmed there are planets around other stars only 31 years ago with the discovery of two rocky planets orbiting a type of neutron star known as a pulsar in 1992.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been an amazing ride since then.  As of today, we’ve discovered over 5,000 extrasolar planets of all shapes and sizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever humans start cataloging and classifying things, whether it be plants, animals, stars or exoplanets, we naturally become interested in the extrema: what is the smallest thing found, what’s the largest?  So, in the spirit of being human, let’s take a look at the largest exoplanet found so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the NASA exoplanet archive, HAT-P-67 b holds the distinction of being the largest exoplanet in terms of size.  With exoplanet classification, one always needs to be careful - especially when it comes to size and mass - because there is a fuzzy boundary with large planets where if they become too large, they are considered a brown dwarf star.  This is a body that almost made it to star status but doesn’t have enough mass or material for nuclear fusion to take place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HAT-P-67-b seems to fit the bill.  It is 1,200 light years from Earth and has a radius that is a little over twice that of Jupiters’.  It orbits its host star very closely, only 10 million kilometers away and has a year that is almost 5 days long.  The star itself,  HAT-P-67, is an F-type star that is one and a half times the mass of the Sun and about two and a half times larger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planets like this are relatively easy to find using the transit method.  Large planets that eclipse their stars many times a month can be spotted using space telescopes like TESS because they are looking at an area of the sky for a limited amount of time and they can see many transits during that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, it’s very hard to see a long period planet, one that takes many hundreds of days to transit its star.  A planet like Earth, for example, would only make one transit in 365 days to a distant observer so they would need to stare out at our Sun for a long time, especially if they wanted multiple transits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But HAT-P-67-b was easy to spot.  It was discovered in 2017 and since it transits so often confirmation was relatively quick.  Because of its low density, astronomers consider this planet a Hot-Saturn, with a mass about half that of Jupiters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as habitability goes, unless there are some moons orbiting this planet getting enough warmth to keep water liquid on its surface, there probably isn’t any life here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="exoplanets" /><summary type="html">HAT-P-67-b seems to fit the bill. It is 1,200 light years from Earth and has a radius that is a little over twice that of Jupiters’. It orbits its host star very closely, only 10 million kilometers away and has a year that is almost 5 days long. The star itself, HAT-P-67, is an F-type star that is one and a half times the mass of the Sun and about two and a half times larger.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/HAT-P-67b.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/HAT-P-67b.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>