<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-US"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en-US" /><updated>2023-10-03T15:02:56-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Exoplanet Radio</title><subtitle> Have you ever wondered what lies beyond our solar system? Are there other planets like Earth out there? How do we find them and study them? What can they teach us about ourselves and our place in the universe?  If you are curious about these questions, then Exoplanet Radio is for you. We will explore the fascinating field of exoplanets, the planets that orbit other stars. We will learn about the history and methods of exoplanet discovery, the diversity and characteristics of exoplanets, the challenges and opportunities of exoplanet science, and the implications and prospects of exoplanet life.  Join us on this journey of wonder and discovery, as we venture into the unknown and uncover the secrets of the worlds beyond our solar system.</subtitle><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">TOI 1853 b: A Baffling Planet That Defies Explanation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/toi1853b-baffling-exoplanet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TOI 1853 b: A Baffling Planet That Defies Explanation" /><published>2023-10-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-10-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/toi1853b-baffling-exoplanet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/toi1853b-baffling-exoplanet/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for October 3rd, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/040-weirdest-exoplanet-final/040_WeirdestExoplanet_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/040-weirdest-exoplanet-final/040_WeirdestExoplanet_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meet TOI-1853 b, one of the weirdest exoplanets ever discovered! It’s about the size of Neptune, but four times more massive. It orbits its star so closely that it completes a full orbit in just 1.24 days. This makes it very hot, and it’s located in a region of space known as the “hot Neptune desert,” where astronomers have been looking for Hot Neptunes but unable to find any.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on the one hand, this is great:  we have a Neptune sized planet close to its star where we haven’t seen many.  On the other hand, this is a really strange world.  It’s the size of Neptune sure, but four times more massive than Neptune and about 73 times more massive than Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronomers infer the mass by looking at the wobble of the host star as the planet orbits it.  They get the size by looking at how much the host star’s light dimmed as it passed in front of it, they can also get the orbital period by looking at the dips several times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here we have a huge and massive planet close to its star.  How did it get there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists are baffled by TOI-1853 b. They’re not sure how it formed, or why it’s so massive. One possibility is that it started out as a gas giant, but lost its atmosphere due to the intense radiation from its star. Another possibility is that it formed in a much cooler region of space, and then migrated closer to its star later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are planets this size all over the place, but not this massive.  One way astronomers infer whether a planet is rocky or not is by it size.  It’s assumed that larger planets are gas giants and one reason we don’t see Hot Neptunes that much is their atmospheres get stripped away.  So if that happened in this case, what could account for the mass involved here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The planet’s mass is too large to have formed from the accumulation of small dust particles from the planet-forming disk. It is also unlikely that the planet formed in its current location, as solids have difficulty condensing there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So astronomers tell us we are left with two rather strange possibilities: either TOI-1853 b is a rocky planet with a thin atmosphere: This is the most likely scenario, as it is consistent with the planet’s density. The atmosphere would be so thin that it would account for only one percent of the planet’s mass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other is its got a rocky core with a thick layer of water: This is less likely, but possible. The water would be in a supercritical state, meaning that it would be both a liquid and a gas. The pressure near the rocky core would force the water to form high-pressure solids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever its origins, TOI-1853 b is a fascinating planet and probably not a very habitable one.  Life here would be bone-crushingly hot.  Imagine weighing 73 times more than you do now and living right next door to the star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of exoplanets is a journey of discovery, and we are only just beginning to scratch the surface of what is possible. Every new planet we find challenges our understanding of how planets form, where they came from, and what they are like.  We have already learned so much about exoplanets in a short period of time. We have discovered planets of all sizes and shapes, orbiting stars of all types. We have found planets made of gas, rock, and even water. We have even found planets that could potentially be habitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with this progress, we are still surprised by what we find.  There is so much more to learn.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="exoplanets" /><summary type="html">Meet TOI-1853 b, one of the weirdest exoplanets ever discovered! It&apos;s about the size of Neptune, but four times more massive. It orbits its star so closely that it completes a full orbit in just 1.24 days. This makes it very hot, and it&apos;s located in a region of space known as the &apos;hot Neptune desert&apos;, where astronomers have been looking for Hot Neptunes but unable to find any.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/TOI-1853b.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/TOI-1853b.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Biosignatures: The Search for Life Beyond Earth</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/science/biosignatures-search-for-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Biosignatures: The Search for Life Beyond Earth" /><published>2023-09-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/science/biosignatures-search-for-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/science/biosignatures-search-for-life/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for September 20th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/039-biosignatures-final/039_Biosignatures_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/039-biosignatures-final/039_Biosignatures_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, scientists have made great strides in the search for extraterrestrial life. They have discovered thousands of exoplanets. And some of them are located in the habitable zone of their star, which means that liquid water could exist on their surface and is essential for life as we know it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The search for life however, is a little more involved than finding planets, measuring their location and distance around the star and figuring out their location within a habitable zone.  Astronomers need more information to learn if life may be there.  The first thing we need to know is whether or not the planet has an atmosphere and thanks to the Webb Space Telescope, we are starting to get a handle on that data point with every observation it makes using its onboard Near Infrared Spectrometer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once astronomers detect an atmosphere, the real fun begins: finding biosignatures.  Biosignatures are indicators of the presence of life, traces left behind by living organisms.  These indicators can be chemical, biological or physical.  An example of a physical biosignature would be things like fossils, and since that requires that we have a physical presence on the planet (we can’t see those from here, not even with JWST), then  we are left with chemical and biological indicators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best examples of biosignatures that we can detect from so far away are atmospheric gasses and organic molecules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain gases, such as oxygen and methane, can be produced by biological processes. However, they can also be produced by non-biological means. For example, oxygen can be produced by photosynthesis, but it can also be produced by geological activity. The presence of atmospheric gases in a planet’s atmosphere could be a sign of life, but it is important to consider other evidence as well, like organic compounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organic molecules are the building blocks of life. They include amino acids, lipids, carbohydrates, and nucleic acids. Organic molecules can be detected in the atmospheres of exoplanets using a technique called spectroscopy. Spectroscopy involves splitting light into its component wavelengths. Organic molecules absorb light at specific wavelengths, so by looking for dips in the spectrum of an exoplanet, scientists can identify the presence of organic molecules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JWST is currently the only instrument we have that can detect biosignatures in this way, it looks at absorbed starlight that has passed through the exoplanet’s atmosphere to see what elements were absorbed.  Just recently, it reported the possibility of the organic molecule dimethyl sulfide in the planet K2-18b, a compound that on Earth is produced primarily by phytoplankton, which are microscopic organisms that live in the ocean. DMS can also be produced by some other biological processes, but it is not known to be produced by anything other than life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DMS is a gas, so it can be detected in the atmospheres of exoplanets using spectroscopy. It is also relatively stable in the atmosphere, so it can accumulate to detectable levels.  All of this makes dimethyl sulfide an ideal biosignature gas.  Other biosignatures that are similar to dimethyl sulfide include: Methanethiol, Dimethyl disulfide, Carbon disulfide and Hydrogen cyanide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that the detection of a single biosignature is not definitive evidence of life. However, the presence of multiple biosignatures in the same place would be very strong evidence. Additionally, if a biosignature is detected in a place where it is unlikely to be produced by non-biological processes, such as in a Martian meteorite, then it is more likely to be a sign of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The James Webb Space Telescope and the future Habitable Worlds Observatory are two powerful tools that we have at our disposal to search for life on other planets. Imagine the day when we discover signs of life beyond Earth. It would be a watershed moment in human history, one that would change our understanding of our place in the universe forever.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html">In recent years, scientists have made great strides in the search for extraterrestrial life. They have discovered thousands of exoplanets. And some of them are located in the habitable zone of their star, which means that liquid water could exist on their surface and is essential for life as we know it. The search for life however, is a little more involved than finding planets, measuring their location and distance around the star and figuring out their location within a habitable zone. Astronomers need more information to learn if life may be there.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Biosignatures.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Biosignatures.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The First Hycean World? JWST’s Discovery of K2-18 b</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/first-hycean-world-jwst-discovery-k218b/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The First Hycean World? JWST’s Discovery of K2-18 b" /><published>2023-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/discoveries/first-hycean-world-jwst-discovery-k218b</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/first-hycean-world-jwst-discovery-k218b/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for September 18th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/038-first-hycean-world-final/038_FirstHyceanWorld_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/038-first-hycean-world-final/038_FirstHyceanWorld_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The James Webb Space Telescope has completed observations of an exoplanet that may contain an ocean-covered surface underneath a hydrogen-rich atmosphere. This discovery provides a fascinating glimpse into a planet unlike anything in our Solar System, and raises interesting prospects about potentially habitable worlds elsewhere in the Universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exoplanet is called K2-18 b, and it’s located about 120 light-years away from us in the constellation Leo. It is bigger than Earth, but not as big as Neptune, putting this exoplanet in a class called sub-Neptunes, one of the most common types of exoplanets we’ve found. It orbits a cool dwarf star called K2-18 in the habitable zone, which means it could have liquid water on its surface. But what’s really amazing is that Webb has detected &lt;strong&gt;methane&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;carbon dioxide&lt;/strong&gt; in its atmosphere. These are carbon-bearing molecules that could indicate the presence of life, or at least some interesting chemistry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Webb used its Near Infrared Spectrograph (NIRSpec) instrument to analyze the light coming from K2-18 b as it passed in front of its star. By looking at how the starlight changed as it filtered through the planet’s atmosphere, Webb could measure the amounts of different molecules in the air. This technique is called &lt;strong&gt;transit spectroscopy&lt;/strong&gt;, and it’s one of the best ways to study exoplanet atmospheres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results showed that K2-18 b has a hydrogen-rich atmosphere with traces of methane and carbon dioxide. There was also a possible detection of another molecule called &lt;strong&gt;dimethyl sulfide&lt;/strong&gt; (DMS), which on Earth is only produced by living organisms. DMS is emitted by phytoplankton in the oceans, and it helps form clouds and regulate the climate. Could K2-18 b have some kind of ocean life that produces DMS? Or is there another explanation for this mysterious molecule?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery of methane and carbon dioxide in K2-18 b’s atmosphere is consistent with the idea that this planet could be a &lt;strong&gt;Hycean&lt;/strong&gt; world. Hycean worlds are a class of exoplanets that have hydrogen-rich atmospheres and water-covered surfaces. They are different from Earth-like worlds, which have nitrogen-rich atmospheres and rocky surfaces. Hycean worlds could be promising targets for finding signs of life but we shouldn’t get too excited just yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While K2-18 b lies in the habitable zone, and is now known to harbor carbon-bearing molecules, this does not necessarily mean that the planet can support life. The planet’s large size — with a radius 2.6 times the radius of Earth, and almost 9 times its mass — means that the planet’s interior likely contains a large mantle of high-pressure ice, like Neptune, but with a thinner hydrogen-rich atmosphere and an ocean surface. Hycean worlds are predicted to have oceans of water. However, it is also possible that the ocean is too hot to be habitable or even be in liquid state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are still many uncertainties and challenges in studying K2-18 b. Webb’s observations are only the first step in exploring this fascinating world, and more data and analysis are needed to confirm and refine the results. Astronomers are planning followup studies using the Mid-Infrared Instrument spectrograph on JWST that they hope will further validate their findings and provide new insights into the environmental conditions on K2-18 b.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These exciting results are the product of just two observations, and there are many more on the way.  We will use the most advanced observatories on Earth and in space to study this planet in more detail. Our ultimate goal is to find an exoplanet with life on it.  If such a world exists, and we can find it, we will have left the cosmic shores of our home and waded just a bit deeper into the universal ocean and found that we are not alone.  And maybe, just maybe, we learn that the universe is teeming with life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="discoveries" /><summary type="html">The James Webb Space Telescope has completed observations of an exoplanet that may contain an ocean-covered surface underneath a hydrogen-rich atmosphere. This discovery provides a fascinating glimpse into a planet unlike anything in our Solar System, and raises interesting prospects about potentially habitable worlds elsewhere in the Universe.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/HyceanWorldK218b.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/HyceanWorldK218b.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Osiris: The Exoplanet That Changed Everything</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/osiris-exoplanet-changed-everything/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Osiris: The Exoplanet That Changed Everything" /><published>2023-09-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/osiris-exoplanet-changed-everything</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/osiris-exoplanet-changed-everything/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for September 15th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/037-osiris-the-planet-that-changed-everything-final/037_OsirisThePlanetThatChangedEverything_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/037-osiris-the-planet-that-changed-everything-final/037_OsirisThePlanetThatChangedEverything_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On September 9, 1999, a team of astronomers from the High Altitude Observatory made a groundbreaking discovery. Using the radial velocity method, they detected a massive, Jupiter-sized planet orbiting a Sun-like star HD 209458. This was the first exoplanet to be discovered using this method, and since that fateful day, this system has become a champion of firsts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The planet is HD 209458 b, and nicknamed “Osiris” after the Egyptian god of the underworld. Osiris is a fitting nickname for this planet, as it is a very hot and hostile world. HD 209458 b orbits its star very closely, and its surface temperature is estimated to be around 1,000 degrees Celsius. This makes it too hot for liquid water to exist on its surface, and it is unlikely to be habitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, this planet is remarkable in many ways.  It occupies first place in a long list of discovery milestones.  Here are the areas Osiris occupies first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is one of the first exoplanets to be discovered using the transit method, which means that astronomers were able to detect it by observing how its star’s light dimmed as the planet passed in front of it. This was a major breakthrough, as it showed that it was possible to directly detect exoplanets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, seeing its transit makes it the first exoplanet to be detected by more than one method: both transit and radial velocity.  Further, it was the first planet to have its orbital speed measured, allowing astronomers to determine its mass directly&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Osiris is also the first exoplanet to have its atmosphere directly detected. In 2001, astronomers using the Hubble Space Telescope were able to measure the absorption of light from HD 209458 b’s atmosphere. This allowed them to identify the presence of sodium and other elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in 2007, astronomers from Lowell Observatory found evidence of water vapor in the upper atmosphere.  Another first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These observations were a major breakthrough in exoplanetary research. It showed that it was possible to learn more about the composition of exoplanet atmospheres, and to search for biosignatures, which are molecules that could be indicative of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Osiris is also the first exoplanet to be observed losing its atmosphere. Astronomers have detected a large plume of hydrogen gas escaping from the planet. This is likely due to the intense heat and stellar winds from the star, stripping it away, leaving a stream of material behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery of the evaporating atmosphere showed that some exoplanets could actually lose their atmospheres, and that this could have a significant impact on their habitability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This exoplanet, some 157 light years away,  has single handedly had a profound impact on our understanding of exoplanets and the search for life beyond Earth. It has advanced our understanding of other worlds outside our solar system perhaps more than any other exoplanet we’ve seen.  It has shown that it is possible to directly detect exoplanets and their atmospheres, find out what they are made of  and that some exoplanets are  losing their atmospheres. This information is essential for our understanding of the diversity of exoplanets and the processes that can affect their habitability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery of HD 209458 b was a major inspiration for the search for life beyond Earth.  Astronomers now realized what was possible when studying other worlds in the distant galaxy.  Although Osiris is not a good candidate for life, its discovery showed that there may be many other exoplanets out there that are more habitable. The detection of water vapor in HD 209458 b’s atmosphere is a promising sign for the search for life beyond Earth, as water is essential for life as we know it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="exoplanets" /><summary type="html">On September 9, 1999, a team of astronomers from the High Altitude Observatory made a groundbreaking discovery. Using the radial velocity method, they detected a massive, Jupiter-sized planet orbiting a Sun-like star HD 209458. This was the first exoplanet to be discovered using this method, and since that fateful day, this system has become a champion of firsts.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/OsirisPlanet.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/OsirisPlanet.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A Glimpse into the Early Stages of Planetary Evolution</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/science/glimpse-early-planet-formation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Glimpse into the Early Stages of Planetary Evolution" /><published>2023-09-14T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/science/glimpse-early-planet-formation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/science/glimpse-early-planet-formation/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for September 14th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/035-trappist-1e-most-habitable-exoplanet-final_202309/036_EarlyStagePlanetaryEvolution_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/035-trappist-1e-most-habitable-exoplanet-final_202309/036_EarlyStagePlanetaryEvolution_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep in the cosmos, NASA’s Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) has discovered four new worlds orbiting a pair of young stars. These planets are providing scientists with a glimpse into a little-understood stage of planetary evolution - the time when atmospheres are being formed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stars TESS looked at are TOI 2076 and TOI 1807 and reside over 130 light-years away with some 30 light-years between them and are located in the northern constellations of Boötes and Canes Venatici. Both are K-type stars, dwarf stars more orange than our Sun, and around 200 million years old, or less than 5% of the Sun’s age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, using data from ESA’s Gaia satellite, scientists showed that the stars are traveling through space in the same direction leading them to think they are related, born from the same cloud of gas..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stars are hyperactive, experiencing stellar flares much more energetic and frequent than those produced by our own Sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around TOI 2076, astronomers discovered three mini-Neptunes, worlds between the diameters of Earth and Neptune&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The innermost planet, TOI 2076 b, circles its star once in only 10 days. The outer planets, c and d, have orbits exceeding 17 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TOI 1807 hosts only one known planet, TOI 1807 b and is the most extreme of the bunch. It orbits its star in an astonishingly fast 13 hours, making it one of the youngest ultra-short period planets ever discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theories suggest that planets initially have thick atmospheres left over from their formation. But stellar radiation can erode these atmospheres, leaving behind rocky cores. Some planets may then develop secondary atmospheres through planetary processes like volcanic activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ages of the TOI 2076 and TOI 1807 systems suggest that their planets may be somewhere in the middle of this atmospheric evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these planets are bombarded with UV radiation, making life here unlikely at this stage in their development.  TOI 2076 b receives 400 times more UV light from its star than Earth does from the Sun – and TOI 1807 b gets around 22,000 times more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists are currently working to measure the planets’ masses, but the interference from their hyperactive stars could make this challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If scientists can discover the planets’ masses, that will help NASA’s James Webb space telescope determine if they have atmospheres and study them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This discovery is a tantalizing glimpse into the early stages of planetary evolution. By studying these worlds, scientists can learn more about how planets form and how their atmospheres develop.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html">Deep in the cosmos, NASA&apos;s Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) has discovered four new worlds orbiting a pair of young stars. These planets are providing scientists with a glimpse into a little-understood stage of planetary evolution - the time when atmospheres are being formed.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/toi_1807_b_still_sml.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/toi_1807_b_still_sml.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">TRAPPIST-1e: The Most Habitable Exoplanet?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/trappist-1e-most-habitable-exoplanet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TRAPPIST-1e: The Most Habitable Exoplanet?" /><published>2023-09-13T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/trappist-1e-most-habitable-exoplanet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/trappist-1e-most-habitable-exoplanet/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for September 13th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/035-trappist-1e-most-habitable-exoplanet-final/035_TRAPPIST-1eMostHabitableExoplanet_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/035-trappist-1e-most-habitable-exoplanet-final/035_TRAPPIST-1eMostHabitableExoplanet_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TRAPPIST-1e is a rocky, close-to-Earth-sized exoplanet orbiting within the habitable zone around the ultra-cool dwarf star TRAPPIST-1 approximately 40 light-years away from Earth in the constellation of Aquarius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the fourth of seven planets in the TRAPPIST-1 system, which is the most studied planetary system outside our own.  Astronomers are intensely interested in these planets because all seven of them are roughly Earth-sized and rocky, and three of them – including TRAPPIST-1e – are located in the habitable zone, where liquid water could exist on their surfaces. it has a mass about half that of the Earths and it’s about the same size.  All of these planets orbit close to the star. It takes only 6 days for this one to complete one orbit, and is so close that it’s about 30 times closer than Earth is to the Sun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TRAPPIST-1e was discovered in 2017 based on observations from various telescopes, including NASA’s Spitzer Space Telescope, which detected the periodic dimming of light from the star as the planet transits, or passes in front of it. Since then, it has been studied by other telescopes, including NASA’s James Webb Space Telescope, which is beginning to probe the  atmosphere and surface conditions of all the planets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TRAPPIST-1e is a fascinating example of how diverse and complex exoplanets can be, and of all the planets in this system, it may be the most suitable exoplanet found yet for life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it is found to have an atmosphere, which would be a huge deal in and of itself and something the Webb Space Telescope is uniquely equipped to do, then by studying it, we can learn more about its climate and potential for habitability. For example, a detailed study by Webb could detect signs of water vapor and ozone in the planet’s atmosphere, which could provide a protective layer against harmful radiation from the star. Webb could also measure the planet’s dayside temperature to give an indication of just what sort of organisms, if any, could survive there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running models of rocky planets like this suggests that TRAPPIST-1e may not be uniformly hot. Because it is tidally locked to its star, meaning it always shows the same face to it, one side of the planet may be much hotter than the other. The night side may be cold enough to freeze water, creating a stark contrast between day and night. The planet may also have strong winds that circulate heat around the globe, creating a more moderate climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, astronomers are starting to think that life on tidally locked planets might even be found nestled in Terminator Zones, the region where the night side of the planet is separated from the day side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TRAPPIST-1e is an enormously promising target for future observations with Webb, not only to further understand the physical characteristics of the planet, but Webb has instruments on board which may be able to detect signs of life if they exist. Astronomers call these biosignatures, and are compounds in the atmosphere that could only be put there by living organisms, such as certain types of methane or oxygen.  This would indicate biological activity on the planet’s surface or subsurface.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="exoplanets" /><summary type="html">TRAPPIST-1e is a rocky, close-to-Earth-sized exoplanet orbiting within the habitable zone around the ultra-cool dwarf star TRAPPIST-1 approximately 40 light-years away from Earth in the constellation of Aquarius.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/TRAPPIST-1d_Surface.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/TRAPPIST-1d_Surface.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Tidally Locked Worlds: Life in the Twilight Zone</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/science/exoplanet-terminator-zones/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tidally Locked Worlds: Life in the Twilight Zone" /><published>2023-09-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/science/exoplanet-terminator-zones</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/science/exoplanet-terminator-zones/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for September 12th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/034-life-in-terminator-zones-final/034_LifeInTerminatorZones_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/034-life-in-terminator-zones-final/034_LifeInTerminatorZones_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on our experience here on Earth, we know life here to be tenacious and ubiquitous.  Even in the harshest climates, if we look hard enough, we can usually find some sort of life there.  We are hoping the same is true on worlds around other stars, and recent research has begun looking into the question of whether life on other worlds could exist in the most inhospitable environs: the terminator zone of tidally locked planets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All planets that orbit a star have a terminator zone.  This is the band of shadow that marks the night side of a planet and the day side.  On most planets, the terminator moves along the surface as it rotates, but one a tidally locked planet, the terminator stays over the same spot all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tidal locking is a phenomenon that occurs when a planet rotates at the same speed as it orbits its star, so it always shows the same face to it. This happens when the gravitational pull of the star is stronger than the rotational force of the planet, and it causes the planet to slow down until it reaches a stable state. You might be familiar with this effect from our own moon, which is tidally locked to Earth and always shows us the same side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if a planet is tidally locked to its star? Well, that would create a huge contrast in temperatures between the two sides of the planet. The day side would be constantly exposed to the star’s heat and light, while the night side would be in perpetual darkness and cold. Depending on how close the planet is to its star, the day side could be hot enough to melt rocks, while the night side could be cold enough to freeze water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is a region in between, called the terminator zone, where things get more interesting. The terminator zone is a band that separates the day from the night, where the temperatures are more moderate and could allow liquid water to exist. And where there is water, there could be life, right? Well, maybe. It depends on a lot of factors, such as the type and size of the star, the amount of water on the planet, and the presence of an atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some scientists have been studying these terminator zones on exoplanets, especially those that orbit dim red dwarf stars, which are very common in our galaxy. Red dwarf stars are smaller and cooler than our sun, but they can still emit powerful flares and radiation that could harm life on nearby planets. However, some of these planets could have habitable climates in their terminator zones, if they have enough water but not too much, and if they have rocky surfaces instead of global oceans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does water and surface matter? Well, water is essential for life as we know it, but too much water could create a runaway greenhouse effect that would make the planet too hot for life. On the other hand, too little water could make the planet too dry and barren for life. A rocky surface could help regulate the temperature and provide nutrients for life, while an ocean-covered surface could make the planet more uniform and boring for life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is an interesting idea, there are still a lot of unknowns and challenges for life to survive on these extreme worlds. For example, how would life cope with the constant light or darkness? How would it deal with the strong winds and storms that could occur in the terminator zone? How would it adapt to the possible volcanic activity on the day side or the ice formation on the night side? How would it communicate and evolve in such diverse environments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are some of the questions that astronomers hope to answer in the future, as they search for signs of life on these exotic planets.  Using telescopes like the James Webb Space Telescope and the future Habitable Worlds Telescope, maybe one day we will find out that we are not alone in this vast universe, and that life can thrive in places we never imagined.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html">Based on our experience here on Earth, we know life here to be tenacious and ubiquitous. Even in the harshest climates, if we look hard enough, we can usually find some sort of life there. We are hoping the same is true on worlds around other stars, and recent research has begun looking into the question of whether life on other worlds could exist in the most inhospitable environs: the terminator zone of tidally locked planets.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/TerminatorZoneExoplanet" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/TerminatorZoneExoplanet" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What is the Habitable Worlds Observatory?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/science/habitable-worlds-observatory/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is the Habitable Worlds Observatory?" /><published>2023-09-08T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/science/habitable-worlds-observatory</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/science/habitable-worlds-observatory/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for September 8th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/033-what-is-hwo-final/033_WhatIsHWO_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/033-what-is-hwo-final/033_WhatIsHWO_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no question that humanity is making fast progress in understanding, cataloging and classifying planets around other stars.  So far we’ve found over five thousand five hundred of them.  But let’s face it, we really want to know, maybe more than anything else, whether these planets have any life on them and whether they are habitable for us to, maybe, live on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding habitable worlds has been a driving passion since we first learned there were other planets out there, and to find them, we are going to need a dedicated instrument that does nothing else but tries to locate and characterize them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s where the Habitable Worlds Observatory comes in.  NASA says  “HWO is a concept for a NASA flagship mission, as recommended by the 2020 Astrophysics Decadal Survey, that would pursue a breadth of astrophysics goals, including searching for and characterizing potentially habitable planets beyond our solar system.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2020 Astrophysics Decadal Survey - this is the body that helps astronomers prioritize what science they want to learn over the next ten years and recommends what to build to achieve those science goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They recommended HWO as NASA’s next flagship Astrophysics mission after the Nancy Grace Roman Space Telescope. HWO would be the first NASA mission designed specifically to look for signs of life on potentially habitable exoplanets, all while contributing to our broader understanding of the cosmos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronomers from different institutions and agencies are convening now to decide what this telescope needs to be able to do in order to fulfill this mission.  This project is just getting started but it’s not starting from scratch.  Much work has already been done planning for another mission with a remarkably similar name: the Habitable Exoplanets Mission or HabEx.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HabEx was planned with virtually identical science goals in mind and the work done there will most likely be included with HWO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s you and I think for a minute, as a start, some of the things the observatory must be able to do, have the angular resolution to resolve the planet, which means that blocking out the light of the star is crucial.  This means HWO will probably have either an onboard coronagraph, or a starshade will be placed between the spacecraft and the star system being studied to block out the host star so we can see the reflected light from the planet.  That’s number 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number 2: There will undoubtedly be a spectrograph of some sort that allows astronomers to tell if there is an atmosphere, and if so, what it’s made of.  It is that spectrum that will tell us the compounds that exist that might make the exoplanet habitable and if life might already be there.  Astronomers refer to these compounds as biosignatures: things that exist in the air that could only be put there by living organisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there is no timetable for launch of this amazing mission yet, NASA is starting to get to work on our next flagship mission to study life elsewhere.  After the launch and deployment of the Nancy Grace Roman Space Telescope, the Habitable Worlds Observatory will be our next gateway to finding life on other worlds.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html">Finding habitable worlds has been a driving passion since we first learned there were other planets out there, and to find them, we are going to need a dedicated instrument that does nothing else but tries to locate and characterize them.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/StarshadeConcept.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/StarshadeConcept.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">TESS’s Breakthrough Discovery of Long-Period Exoplanets TOI 4600 b and c</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/TESS-finds-long-period-exoplanet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TESS’s Breakthrough Discovery of Long-Period Exoplanets TOI 4600 b and c" /><published>2023-09-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/discoveries/TESS-finds-long-period-exoplanet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/TESS-finds-long-period-exoplanet/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for September 7th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/032-tesslongest-period-planet-final_202309/032_TESSLongestPeriodPlanet_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/032-tesslongest-period-planet-final_202309/032_TESSLongestPeriodPlanet_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human beings have discovered over five thousand five hundred exoplanets.  Over 80 percent of them have orbits shorter than 50 days which would place them at over twice as close to their star as Mercury is to the Sun.  Some are even closer.  Recent observations from TESS however have found one with an orbit of 82 days and another measured in hundreds of days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why are we finding so many toasty worlds, so close to the star?  There are likely just as many planets farther out from their star that orbit with periods measured in hundreds of days, like the Earth does, but the reason we’ve seen so many of these types of planets comes down to the limits of our telescopes and how we are observing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two of the most popular ways of finding exoplanets right now are the transit and radial velocity methods.  To use them, we have to actually watch the planet move around the star or between us and the star, and waiting around for that to happen is expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Telescopes are in high demand, and to stare at a star for hundreds of days hoping to see a planet go around is not practical with the way telescope time is allocated, so we are only getting good data from planets that whiz around their star in a short time.  But of course astronomers realize that’s not the whole picture, there are no doubt many long period exoplanets out there, we just have to deploy an observing system capable of finding them.  More on that in a minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to TESS: The Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite.  It only looks at an area of the sky for about a month before it moves on to other parts of the sky.  The idea was to sacrifice getting complete orbits of planets for partial ones, all the while imaging the entire sky and flagging potential transits as “Objects of Interest” for further study by other telescopes.  TESS has amassed thousands of Objects of Interest, or TOI’s since its launch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of them, TOI-4600 is a rare system containing two long-period planets orbiting a nearby star that is 815 light years from Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TESS team discovered that the star hosts an inner planet with an orbit of 82 days, similar to that of Mercury, while a second outer planet circles every 482 days, placing its distance from its star somewhere between the orbits of Earth and Mars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both planets are likely gas giants, similar to Jupiter and Saturn, though the composition of the inner planet may be more of a mix of gas and ice. The two planets bridge the gap between “hot Jupiters” — the toasty, short-orbit planets that make up the majority of exoplanet discoveries — and the much colder, longer-period gas giants in our solar system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronomers found the longer period planet by stacking up data from past searches of the sky to build up the light curve.  TESS has scanned the entire sky once already.  They also looked at the system using ground-based telescopes to get a fuller picture of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What TESS is really good at though is for short searches over a wide area of sky.  This method of observing is great for getting these short period exoplanets.  An ideal scenario would be to look at the entire sky for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily we have just such a program starting very soon with the Vera Rubin Telescope.  It will survey the entire sky several times a week looking for all sorts of things, one of them being exoplanet transits.  And it will do if for years, allowing astronomers to build a deep view of the heavens over a long time, seeing dips in brightness across the heavens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our window to more worlds around other stars is about to get a lot bigger.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="discoveries" /><summary type="html">Human beings have discovered over five thousand five hundred exoplanets. Over 80 percent of them have orbits shorter than 50 days which would place them at over twice as close to their star as Mercury is to the Sun. Some are even closer. Recent observations from TESS however have found one with an orbit of 82 days and another measured in hundreds of days.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/TOI-4600System.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/TOI-4600System.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Astronomers Confirm Proxima Centauri b is Not a Transiting Exoplanet</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/proxima-centauri-b-not-transiting-exoplanet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Astronomers Confirm Proxima Centauri b is Not a Transiting Exoplanet" /><published>2023-09-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/discoveries/proxima-centauri-b-not-transiting-exoplanet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/proxima-centauri-b-not-transiting-exoplanet/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for September 6th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/031-proximab-no-transit-final/031_ProximabNoTransit_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/031-proximab-no-transit-final/031_ProximabNoTransit_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronomers have recently concluded an observation study of the closest exoplanet to Earth, Proxima Centauri b and found that the planet does not transit its star.  These observations settle a question that astronomers have been asking since the exoplanet’s discovery in 2016 using the radial velocity method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proxima Centauri b was discovered in August 2016 at the European Southern Observatory using a technique that watches the wobble of a star as the gravity from a planet in orbit around it, pulls the star to and fro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By watching the star in this way, astronomers can tell several things: how many planets are there (in this case there’s just one), how massive they are (proxima b has roughly the same mass as the Earth), and how fast they go around the star (proxima b takes 11 days to go around the star once).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is, astronomers also want a transit; they have never seen the planet pass between us and the star, leading astronomers to take a longer look at our nearest exoplanet neighbor.  Why is observing a transit such a big deal? When a planet passes in front of the star the light from that star can give us clues to the physical size of the planet, but more importantly, the James Webb Space Telescope can measure that light and tell us if there is an atmosphere present on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would be great news because not only is Proxima b our closest neighbor at a little over four light years, but it lies in the habitable zone of Proxima Centauri.  If proxima b had an atmosphere, and if it had water, then that water could be liquid and may sustain life as we understand it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So measuring a transit of Proxima Centauri b would give us very important data about the habitability of the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results of this recent study were disappointing however.  Looking at the system with data from the Spitzer Space telescope and instruments in operation on the ground at the European Southern Observatory, astronomers confirmed that the exoplanet, proxima centauri b does not transit the star, not even partially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly little has been learned about proxima b since its discovery. We don’t know how old it is,  whether it has an atmosphere, whether it is tidally locked, nor it’s precise size.  But because it is so close, it provides one of the best opportunities for learning about Earth-sized worlds around M-class dwarf stars.  This is important because there are a lot of systems like this and having one in our celestial backyard is an ideal laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronomers estimate that planets less than ten times the mass of Earth occur around M-class stars at a rate of about one per star. There is at least one rocky planet around every M dwarf, and there are more M-class stars than any other star out there.  The more we understand the Proxima Centauri system, the more we understand most of the exoplanets in our galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although a transit event would have been ideal, we can still learn a lot about Proxima b from other sources of information.  For example, the star Proxima Centauri is a flaring M-class dwarf, and it flares, a lot,  over 60 times a day.  This, coupled with the assumption that it is tidally locked to the star, and that it orbits very close, the chance of keeping an atmosphere is low and that would make habitability seem rather a rather remote possibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to keep looking, observing, measuring and analyzing the closest exoplanet system to the Earth.  We have in our celestial backyard a pristine laboratory for understanding the question of habitability on planets around other stars.  Most of the planets in our galaxy orbit M-class stars like this, and we are sitting right next door to one.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="discoveries" /><summary type="html">Proxima Centauri b does not pass between us and the star, astronomers confirm. This will make determining habitability harder.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/Proxima_b.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/Proxima_b.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>