<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-US"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en-US" /><updated>2023-08-18T07:59:51-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Exoplanet Radio</title><subtitle> Have you ever wondered what lies beyond our solar system? Are there other planets like Earth out there? How do we find them and study them? What can they teach us about ourselves and our place in the universe?  If you are curious about these questions, then Exoplanet Radio is for you. We will explore the fascinating field of exoplanets, the planets that orbit other stars. We will learn about the history and methods of exoplanet discovery, the diversity and characteristics of exoplanets, the challenges and opportunities of exoplanet science, and the implications and prospects of exoplanet life.  Join us on this journey of wonder and discovery, as we venture into the unknown and uncover the secrets of the worlds beyond our solar system.</subtitle><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">KELT-9b: The Hottest Known Exoplanet</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/kelt9b-hottest-known-exoplanet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="KELT-9b: The Hottest Known Exoplanet" /><published>2023-08-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/kelt9b-hottest-known-exoplanet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/kelt9b-hottest-known-exoplanet/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 18th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/023-kelt-9b-hottest-exoplanet-final/023_KELT-9bHottestExoplanet_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/023-kelt-9b-hottest-exoplanet-final/023_KELT-9bHottestExoplanet_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this episode, we are going to take a look at an extreme planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kelt-9b is a gas giant planet that orbits a star 670 light-years from Earth. It is so close to its star that its dayside temperature is 7,800 degrees Fahrenheit (4,300 degrees Celsius), hotter than some stars. This heat is so intense that it rips apart the molecules in the planet’s atmosphere, including hydrogen gas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But its star, called KELT-9, is even hotter – a blue A-type star that is likely unraveling the planet through evaporation.  The KELT-9 is only 300 million years old, which is young for a star. It is more than twice as large, and nearly twice as hot, as our sun. Given that the planet’s atmosphere is constantly blasted with high levels of ultraviolet radiation, the planet may even be shedding a tail of evaporated planetary material like a comet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery of Kelt-9b was announced in 2017 by a team of astronomers using the Kilodegree Extremely Little Telescope (KELT) system. The KELT system is a network of two robotic telescopes that are used to search for exoplanets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kelt-9b is a very massive planet, with a mass that is about three times that of Jupiter. The heat is caused by the proximity of the planet to its star. Kelt-9b orbits its star in just 36 hours, which means that it is constantly bathed in the star’s heat.  The planet is also unusual in that it orbits perpendicular to the spin axis of the star. That would be analogous to the planet orbiting perpendicular to the plane of our solar system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extreme heat of Kelt-9b has a profound effect on its atmosphere. The heat is so intense that it rips apart the molecules in the atmosphere, including hydrogen gas. This process is called photodissociation. The broken-up atoms then flow to the nightside of the planet, where it is cooler. On the nightside, the atoms can recombine to form molecules again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With each orbit, KELT-9 b twice experiences the full range of stellar temperatures, producing what amounts to a peculiar seasonal sequence. The planet experiences “summer” when it swings over each hot pole and “winter” when it passes over the star’s cooler midsection. So KELT-9 b experiences two summers and two winters every orbit, with each season about nine hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process is happening constantly on Kelt-9b, which means that the planet’s atmosphere is constantly being recycled. This makes it very difficult for any life to exist on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of Kelt-9b and other hot Jupiters is helping astronomers to better understand the formation and evolution of exoplanets. It is also helping them to learn more about the limits of habitability in the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to being the hottest exoplanet known, Kelt-9b is also one of the brightest. This makes it a valuable target for further study. Astronomers are using telescopes like the James Webb Space Telescope to learn more about the atmosphere of Kelt-9b.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of Kelt-9b is just one example of the exciting discoveries that are being made in the field of exoplanet research. As astronomers continue to study these distant worlds, they are learning more about the diversity of planets that exist beyond our solar system. This knowledge is helping us to better understand our own place in the universe.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="exoplanets" /><summary type="html">Kelt-9b is a gas giant planet that orbits a star 670 light-years from Earth. It is so close to its star that its dayside temperature is 7,800 degrees Fahrenheit (4,300 degrees Celsius), hotter than some stars. This heat is so intense that it rips apart the molecules in the planet&apos;s atmosphere, including hydrogen gas</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/KELT-9b.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/KELT-9b.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">HAT-P-67 b: The Largest Exoplanet Known</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/largest-known-exoplanet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="HAT-P-67 b: The Largest Exoplanet Known" /><published>2023-08-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/largest-known-exoplanet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/largest-known-exoplanet/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 17th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/022-the-largest-exopplanet-final/022_TheLargestExopplanet_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/022-the-largest-exopplanet-final/022_TheLargestExopplanet_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exoplanet astronomy is a new science, astronomers have only confirmed there are planets around other stars only 31 years ago with the discovery of two rocky planets orbiting a type of neutron star known as a pulsar in 1992.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been an amazing ride since then.  As of today, we’ve discovered over 5,000 extrasolar planets of all shapes and sizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever humans start cataloging and classifying things, whether it be plants, animals, stars or exoplanets, we naturally become interested in the extrema: what is the smallest thing found, what’s the largest?  So, in the spirit of being human, let’s take a look at the largest exoplanet found so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the NASA exoplanet archive, HAT-P-67 b holds the distinction of being the largest exoplanet in terms of size.  With exoplanet classification, one always needs to be careful - especially when it comes to size and mass - because there is a fuzzy boundary with large planets where if they become too large, they are considered a brown dwarf star.  This is a body that almost made it to star status but doesn’t have enough mass or material for nuclear fusion to take place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HAT-P-67-b seems to fit the bill.  It is 1,200 light years from Earth and has a radius that is a little over twice that of Jupiters’.  It orbits its host star very closely, only 10 million kilometers away and has a year that is almost 5 days long.  The star itself,  HAT-P-67, is an F-type star that is one and a half times the mass of the Sun and about two and a half times larger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planets like this are relatively easy to find using the transit method.  Large planets that eclipse their stars many times a month can be spotted using space telescopes like TESS because they are looking at an area of the sky for a limited amount of time and they can see many transits during that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, it’s very hard to see a long period planet, one that takes many hundreds of days to transit its star.  A planet like Earth, for example, would only make one transit in 365 days to a distant observer so they would need to stare out at our Sun for a long time, especially if they wanted multiple transits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But HAT-P-67-b was easy to spot.  It was discovered in 2017 and since it transits so often confirmation was relatively quick.  Because of its low density, astronomers consider this planet a Hot-Saturn, with a mass about half that of Jupiters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as habitability goes, unless there are some moons orbiting this planet getting enough warmth to keep water liquid on its surface, there probably isn’t any life here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="exoplanets" /><summary type="html">HAT-P-67-b seems to fit the bill. It is 1,200 light years from Earth and has a radius that is a little over twice that of Jupiters’. It orbits its host star very closely, only 10 million kilometers away and has a year that is almost 5 days long. The star itself, HAT-P-67, is an F-type star that is one and a half times the mass of the Sun and about two and a half times larger.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/HAT-P-67b.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/exoplanets/HAT-P-67b.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">JWST Takes First Direct Image of an Exoplanet</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/jwst-takes-first-direct-image-exoplanet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JWST Takes First Direct Image of an Exoplanet" /><published>2023-08-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/discoveries/jwst-takes-first-direct-image-exoplanet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/jwst-takes-first-direct-image-exoplanet/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 16th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/021-jwstdirectly-image-exoplanet-final/021_JWSTDirectlyImageExoplanet_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/021-jwstdirectly-image-exoplanet-final/021_JWSTDirectlyImageExoplanet_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launch and deployment of the James Webb Space Telescope in July 2022, marked the beginning of a new era in exoplanet science.  Never before had humanity launched a more powerful and technologically advanced instrument into orbit that had the capabilities that JWST does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was designed to satisfy many science requirements, among them: to measure the properties of exoplanet atmospheres and even resolve their planetary disks.  As you can imagine, imaging exoplanets directly is not easy.  JWST does it by masking out the bright light of the host star using a one-of-a-kind coronagraph.  Coronagraphs are easy to visualize, they are just masks that block light from some part of the camera sensor.  Some solar telescopes for example use a little metal disk to block out the sun, but in true JWST style, the coronagraphs on Webb take things beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JWST has 248,000 microshutters that can open and close individually and when used in unison, create a mask that can cover the disk of a star.  There are five masks on the infrared camera and four on the infrared spectrograph.  When the light from the bright host star is blocked by these masks, the reflected light from the planet can be seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how well does it work?  Has JWST imaged a planet yet?  Yep.  Sure has.  Just a few months after deployment, astronomers have used NASA’s James Webb Space Telescope to take a direct image of a planet outside our solar system. The exoplanet is a gas giant, meaning it has no rocky surface and could not be habitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a transformative moment, not only for Webb but also for exoplanet astronomy generally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exoplanet in Webb’s image, called HIP 65426 b, is about six to 12 times the mass of Jupiter, and these observations could help narrow that down even further. It is young as planets go — about 15 to 20 million years old, compared to our 4.5-billion-year-old Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since HIP 65426 b is about 100 times farther from its host star than Earth is from the Sun, it is sufficiently distant that Webb can easily separate the planet from the star in the image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking direct images of exoplanets is challenging because stars are so much brighter than planets. The HIP 65426 b planet is more than 10,000 times fainter than its host star in the near-infrared, and a few thousand times fainter than that in the mid-infrared. Obtaining this image is like digging for space treasure and finding it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Webb Space Telescope managed to do it, just as designed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s most exciting is that we’ve only just begun. There are many more images of exoplanets to come that will shape our overall understanding of their physics, chemistry, and planet formation. We may even discover previously unknown planets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="discoveries" /><summary type="html">Just a few months after deployment, astronomers have used NASA’s James Webb Space Telescope to take a direct image of a planet outside our solar system. The exoplanet is a gas giant, meaning it has no rocky surface and could not be habitable</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/jwst_in_space-cc.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/jwst_in_space-cc.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">TRAPPIST-1d: A World on the Edge of Life</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/trappist1d-world-edge-of-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TRAPPIST-1d: A World on the Edge of Life" /><published>2023-08-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/trappist1d-world-edge-of-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/trappist1d-world-edge-of-life/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 15th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/020-trappist-1d-the-edgeof-life-final/020_TRAPPIST-1dTheEdgeofLife_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/020-trappist-1d-the-edgeof-life-final/020_TRAPPIST-1dTheEdgeofLife_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tucked inside a quiet solar system, in the area of sky outlined by the constellation Aquarius, orbits a planet named TRAPPIST-1d, the third of seven planets in a system positioned 41 light years from our vantage point.  TRAPPIST-1d is a rocky, Earth-like planet, meaning that it is roughly the same size and mass as our home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TRAPPIST-1d has a radius that is about three quarters the size of Earth, and a comparable mass just a little heavier.  Planets like this are of intense interest to astronomers because they are so like our own.  In many respects, this planet is the most habitable exoplanet found so far.  It is not large enough to retain light gasses like hydrogen and helium, which could destroy nascent life and it is comfortably situated in the star’s habitable zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the TRAPPIST-1 planets are close to its star; the entire system can fit inside the orbit of Mercury.  All of these planets are racing around their home star and TRAPPIST-1d  has a year that is a mere 4 Earth days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, TRAPPIST-1d’s proximity to its host star, merely 2.2 million kilometers, would initially hint that it is a world bathed in lethal radiation.  Orbiting a red dwarf star can be dangerous for any life that might be trying to make it on the surface.  While these stars’ lifetimes are measured in the trillions of years - which is a good thing because it gives life a long time to evolve if its there - their early life is defined by huge stellar activity and raging eruptions that could bake anything living on the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, later on, things settle down and due to being a relatively cool star compared to ours, the light and heat it receives becomes benign, only 4.3% of that which reaches our Earth from our more boisterous Sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This serendipitous combination of distance, host star, and proportion places TRAPPIST-1d in an inintriguing position. At this point in the star’s life its light might heat its surface just enough to sustain liquid water.  But any life trying to make it there must overcome one more obstacle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The close proximity ot TRAPPIST-1d may put the star in a state of tidal locking, this is a condition where the planet’s daily rotation matches its revolution around the star, placing one side always facing the star whilst the other is cloacked in darkness – a stark, perpetual contrast.  Astronomers believe that tidally locked planets may harbor life at the terminator zone of the surface, the line denominating constant darkness with continual heat and radiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this canvas of cosmic chaos and order, TRAPPIST-1d is a tantalizing world. It forces us to abandon our assumptions and welcome the plausibility of life’s existence in corners of the universe we previously dismissed as devoid or hostile.  We wait anxiously for more observations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the apparent silence of the cosmos, TRAPPIST-1d resounds loudly in the ears of our curiosity, a cosmic chant luring us to explore beyond the confines of our own world. In the cosmic theater, 41 light years is a mere stride. As we gaze on these alien lands upon the cosmic horizon, the symphony of the stars resonates within us, a celestial music reminding us of both our insignificance and potential within this infinite cosmic orchestra.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="exoplanets" /><summary type="html">Tucked inside a quiet solar system, in the area of sky outlined by the constellation Aquarius, orbits a planet named TRAPPIST-1d, the third of seven planets in a system positioned 41 light years from our vantage point. TRAPPIST-1d is a rocky, Earth-like planet, meaning that it is roughly the same size and mass as our home.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/TRAPPIST-1d_Surface.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/TRAPPIST-1d_Surface.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Finding Exoplanets with Direct Imaging</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/science/direct-imaging-exoplanets/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finding Exoplanets with Direct Imaging" /><published>2023-08-14T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/science/direct-imaging-exoplanets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/science/direct-imaging-exoplanets/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 14th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/019-direct-imaging-exoplanets-final/019_DirectImagingExoplanets_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/019-direct-imaging-exoplanets-final/019_DirectImagingExoplanets_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons we’ve created Exoplanet Radio is that Exoplanets are awesome.  The idea that there are planets in orbit around stars outside our solar system - and even rogue planets that do not orbit a star meandering through interstellar space - is one that cannot help but capture our imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is, finding them is very hard.  They are small and dim compared to stars so we need to rely on indirect methods to see them like looking for dips in brightness or a wobbling star, or, in the case of rogue planets with no stars, tiny flashes of light from background stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But ideally, we’d like to see them directly, in our telescopes.  Is that possible?  You probably guessed I wouldn’t have brought up the question if the answer wasn’t ‘yes’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, we have discovered over 5000 exoplanets, using transit, radial velocity and microlensing methods. But there is another way to find exoplanets that has only recently been possible: by directly seeing them with our eyes. This is unimaginatively called the direct imaging method, and has revealed some amazing results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here’s the scenario: We see all planets - including those in our solar system - in reflected light from the star.  Starlight shines on a planet and is reflected to our telescopes.  Now imagine trying to see a tiny speck of dust next to a bright light bulb. That is the challenge of direct imaging  planets light years away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The star’s light is so dazzling that it blinds us from seeing the planet’s faint glow. To fix that, astronomers use a special device called a coronagraph, which blocks out the star’s light and lets us see the planet’s light. It is like putting a finger over the light bulb, so we can see the dust speck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this method, astronomers have captured some stunning images of exoplanets, such as 2M1207b, the first exoplanet to be directly imaged, and also the first one to orbit a brown dwarf star, a failed star that is too small to shine. We have also seen four planets orbit around the young star HR8799, in a mesmerizing choreography of motion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Direct imaging is not only beautiful, but also powerful. It can tell us more about the exoplanets than any other method. It has the potential to show us their colors, shapes, sizes, and even their weather patterns. It can reveal their oceans, continents, and maybe even signs of life. It can open our eyes to new worlds and new possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Direct imaging is still a young and evolving technique, but it has already shown us some of the most incredible sights in the universe. As our technology improves, we will be able to see more and more exoplanets with direct imaging, and learn more about them. We will be able to witness the diversity and beauty of these distant worlds, and maybe even find one that is like our own.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html">So here’s the scenario: We see all planets - including those in our solar system - in reflected light from the star. Starlight shines on a planet and is reflected to our telescopes. Now imagine trying to see a tiny speck of dust next to a bright light bulb. That is the challenge of direct imaging exoplanets light years away.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/eso0515a_2m107.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/eso0515a_2m107.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">James Webb Space Telescope Observes New Type of Brown Dwarf</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/jwst-observes-new-brown-dwarf/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="James Webb Space Telescope Observes New Type of Brown Dwarf" /><published>2023-08-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/jwst-observes-new-brown-dwarf</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/exoplanets/jwst-observes-new-brown-dwarf/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 11th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/018-jwstnew-type-brown-dwarf-final/018_JWSTNewTypeBrownDwarf_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/018-jwstnew-type-brown-dwarf-final/018_JWSTNewTypeBrownDwarf_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a planet that is so far away from us that it takes 40 years for its light to reach us. Now imagine that this planet has not one, but two stars that it orbits around. And finally, imagine that this planet has clouds made of sand particles that change the brightness of its atmosphere wildly as they move in the air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This planet, VHS 1256 b, has recently been observed by the James Webb Space Telescope  and it is a very interesting world. It is not like any of the planets in our solar system, or even like most of the planets that we have found outside our solar system. It is a type of planet called a brown dwarf, which is somewhere between a giant gas planet and a small star. Brown dwarfs are very hard to study, because they are very faint and cold compared to stars, and very bright and hot compared to planets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But VHS 1256 b is different from other brown dwarfs, because it has some features that make it easier to observe. First of all, it is very young, only 150 million years old, which is much younger than our sun, at 4.6 billion years old. This means that it is still hot and glowing from its formation, and has not cooled down yet, making it very bright in the infrared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, it is very far away from its two stars, about four times farther than Pluto is from our sun. This means that it does not get much light or heat from its host stars, and also that its light does not get mixed with the light from its stars when we look at it from Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, it has a very fast rotation, spinning around once every 22 hours. This means that its atmosphere is constantly changing and moving, creating different patterns and colors on its surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These features make VHS 1256 b a perfect target for the James Webb Space Telescope. JWST is the most powerful and advanced telescope ever built, and it can see things that no other telescope can see. It can see infrared light, which is invisible to our eyes, but which reveals a lot of information about the temperature, composition, and structure of objects in space. It can also see very faint and distant objects, like VHS 1256 b, with great clarity and detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using Webb, scientists have been able to see some amazing things about VHS 1256 b’s atmosphere. They have found that it has clouds made of silicate dust, which are tiny particles of rocks like quartz or sand. These clouds are very high in the air, where the temperature is about 1,500 degrees Fahrenheit (830 degrees Celsius), which is way hotter than an oven. The clouds have different sizes of dust grains, some as small as smoke and some as large as sand. The size of the dust grains affects how they reflect and scatter light, creating different colors and brightness levels on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Webb has also been able to see what gasses are in VHS 1256 b’s air. It has found water, methane, carbon monoxide, and maybe carbon dioxide. This is the first time that so many gases are found on a brown dwarf or a planet outside our solar system. These gasses tell us about the chemistry and history of the planet, and how it formed and evolved over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VHS 1256 b is a fascinating example of how diverse and complex the universe is. It shows us that there are many types of planets out there that we have not seen before, and that we can learn a lot from them using new technologies like Webb. It also challenges us to think about what makes a planet a planet, and what makes life possible on a planet. VHS 1256 b may not be habitable for us or any other life forms that we know of, but it may have some secrets or surprises that we have not discovered yet.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="exoplanets" /><summary type="html">VHS 1256 b is a fascinating example of how diverse and complex the universe is. It shows us that there are many types of planets out there that we have not seen before, and that we can learn a lot from them using new technologies like JWST.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/STScI-01GVGH2NDBHPT12FQPQA6AFZGC.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/STScI-01GVGH2NDBHPT12FQPQA6AFZGC.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Life in the Dark: How Moons of Rogue Planets Could Harbor Life</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/science/life-in-the-dark/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Life in the Dark: How Moons of Rogue Planets Could Harbor Life" /><published>2023-08-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/science/life-in-the-dark</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/science/life-in-the-dark/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 10th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/017-life-in-the-dark-final/017_LifeInTheDark_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/017-life-in-the-dark-final/017_LifeInTheDark_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There might be many places in the universe where habitable conditions can exist.  But just having those conditions isn’t enough, in order for life to thrive, it also needs stability.  It took life on Earth about a billion years to appear, but to last, it also needed a cradle that was safe and stable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Habitability and stability don’t necessarily need to come from a nearby star.  It could be sufficient to have an atmosphere, some water and a source of heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our galaxy, there are many planets that wander alone in the dark, without a star to orbit. These rogue planets could have formed from the same material that makes stars, or they could have been kicked out of their original star systems by gravitational interactions. Some of these rogue planets could have moons which remain in tow, and these moons could be more than just cold and barren rocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a moon has a thick atmosphere, such as carbon dioxide, and some water, it could create a greenhouse effect that traps heat and keeps the surface warm. The heat could also come from the tidal forces of the planet, which stretch and squeeze the moon as it orbits around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This same process is going on in Saturn’s moon Enceladus and Jupiter’s moon Europa.  A sufficiently thick, heat-trapping atmosphere, might keep the surface warm enough for water to remain liquid.  That water could come from chemical reactions with the carbon dioxide and hydrogen in the atmosphere, initiated by changed particles from space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how long can such a moon sustain life? The tidal forces that heat up the moon also make its orbit more circular over time, which reduces the friction and the heat. Eventually, the moon will cool down and freeze over. The question is: will life have enough time to emerge and evolve before that happens?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on our own planet’s history, life took about a billion years to appear on Earth. Can a moon of a rogue planet last that long? Astronomers are starting to believe the answer depends on how thick the atmosphere is. A thicker atmosphere means more heat retention and more stability. A thin atmosphere means more heat loss and more variability. According to computer simulations, a moon with a thick atmosphere could stay warm for anywhere from 300 million to almost 2 billion years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s enough time for life to have a chance to arise and hopefully thrive on a moon of a rogue planet. However, before we get too far ahead of ourselves, let’s remember that warmth and water might not be enough to let living organisms appear. There are many factors that influence the origin and evolution of life, and we don’t fully understand them yet.  But it’s probably safe to say that moons of free-floating planets will not be the most favorable places for life to arise.  Stars, because they are so powerful and long lived, are still the best nurseries for any nascent life on an exoplanet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, there are many environments in our universe which are very different from what we have here on Earth.  It is important that we investigate them all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html">If a moon has a thick atmosphere, such as carbon dioxide, and some water, it could create a greenhouse effect that traps heat and keeps the surface warm. The heat could also come from the tidal forces of the planet, which stretch and squeeze the moon as it orbits around it.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/ExoMoon.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/ExoMoon.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How Long Would it Take to Travel to Proxima Centauri b?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/science/how-long-to-proxima-b/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Long Would it Take to Travel to Proxima Centauri b?" /><published>2023-08-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/science/how-long-to-proxima-b</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/science/how-long-to-proxima-b/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 9th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/016-travel-time-proximab-final/016_TravelTimeProximab_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/016-travel-time-proximab-final/016_TravelTimeProximab_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the course of this podcast, we’ve established the idea that there are a lot of exoplanets in our universe.  Some are big, some are small, some are close to their stars, others are very far away.  One thing we haven’t said much about though is just how far away they all are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people feel that it’s very important for humanity’s long term survival that we become a multiplanet species.  Traveling to and possibly even inhabiting other planets in our solar system is not only possible with our current levels of technology, but compared to going to the stars, it’s downright easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about traveling to exoplanets?  Can we reach the stars?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the way things are now with our rocket technology, it’s not looking good.  Let’s use traveling to the closest exoplanet to us as an example.  How long would it take to get to Proxima Centaui b?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get anywhere in the galaxy at anything resembling a reasonable time, we need to go fast - some fraction of light speed would be best.  Proxima Centauri is 4.3 light years away, so even the fastest thing we know about - light - takes years to get there.  So far, the fastest spaceship we have ever built is the New Horizons Probe and it’s going along at 58,000 kilometers per hour. At that speed, it would take roughly 80,000 years to get to Proxima Centauri b.  The Voyager 1 and II probes are also going fast, they aren’t heading toward Proxima b, but they are going really fast too, 61,000 and 55,000 kilometers per hour respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if they were pointed at Proxima b, then we’re looking at about 80,000 years for the Voyager probes too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, the Parker Solar Probe managed speeds of 700,000 kilometers per hour at closest approach around the Sun, but it did that at very short intervals.  Still that’s .06% the speed of light, so we’re getting there, but it wasn’t sustainable for long distance stellar flight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll need to do a lot better than that if we want to get to the closest exoplanet to us in any reasonable amount of time.  Chemical rockets, the kind we’re using right now, won’t get anywhere near fast enough and are very problematic because we need to carry all that fuel with us as we go, and that reduces efficiency a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fusion rockets are very promising, but we don’t have any of those yet.  Still, if we could use the energy of fusing Helium-3 isotopes and Deuterium we might be able to reach sustained speeds on order of the Parker Solar Probe of 0.06% the speed of light and arrive at Proxima b in about 25,000 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sweet spot would be if we could somehow attain speeds of about 10% the speed of light.  If we could do that, then travel to Proxima b, 4.3 light years away would take 44 years or so.  That’s well within a normal human lifespan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slightly less appealing but still remarkable would be if humanity could achieve 1% light speed.  It would still take 436 years to reach our closest exoplanet, but one can imagine technologies, like cryogenics, that might help us get through the journey intact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Space is big, there’s no doubt about it.  And looking at the big picture, that’s probably a good thing.  Still, it would be nice if we could figure out technologies that can get us to appreciable percentages of light speed to cover these vast interstellar distances in reasonable times.  Of course, we might discover new physics that allows us to traverse the galaxy, but for now we are confined by relativity and technologies that keep us well below light speeds and the distant exoplanets out of our reach.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html">We’ll need to do a lot better than that if we want to get to the closest exoplanet to us in any reasonable amount of time.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/GirlAlienLandscape.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/GirlAlienLandscape.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A Giant Planet Found Orbiting a Small Star</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/giant-planet-around-small-star/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Giant Planet Found Orbiting a Small Star" /><published>2023-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/discoveries/giant-planet-around-small-star</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/giant-planet-around-small-star/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 8th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/015-giant-planet-small-star-final/015_GiantPlanetSmallStar_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/015-giant-planet-small-star-final/015_GiantPlanetSmallStar_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A massive, Jupiter-sized exoplanet has been discovered orbiting a small, low-mass star and this discovery is challenging theories on how planets form around their stars. The planet, called TOI-4860 b, is about the same size as Jupiter and orbits its star once every 1.5 Earth days, classifying it as a warm Jupiter. This is unusual because planets this large are not supposed to form around low-mass stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exoplanet orbits the red dwarf star TOI-4860. Located in the constellation of Corvus the crow some 261 light years away, TOI-4860 has a mass equivalent to just around a third of our Sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get this large, the team that discovered TOI-4860 b believes that the planet may have formed from a disk of material that was enriched in heavy elements. This enrichment could have helped the planet to grow to its current size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery of TOI-4860 b challenges our understanding of how planets form. The traditional model of planet formation says that planets form from disks of gas and dust that surround young stars. The amount of material in these disks is thought to be related to the mass of the star. So, a low-mass star would have a less massive disk, and therefore would not be able to form a planet as large as TOI-4860 b.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, astronomers believe that there may be another way for planets to form around low-mass stars. These planets may have formed from the merger of smaller planets. This would require a very specific set of circumstances, but it is possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TOI-4860 b was first spotted by NASA’s Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS), which hunts planets outside the solar system by looking for tiny drops in the brightness of light emitted by stars. Those dimmings are caused as an orbiting planet crosses between the host star and our telesocpes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery of TOI-4860 b is a reminder that we still have a lot to learn about how planets form. This discovery is just one more piece of the puzzle, and it will be exciting to see what else we learn in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding planets in locations we don’t expect and in regions that defy our current understanding is an important reason why astronomers scan the heavens in search of other worlds.  The universe is a vast and mysterious place and we have only just begun the quest for life in the universe and it all starts with these observations, performed by vigilant ground and space-based telescopes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="discoveries" /><summary type="html">Finding planets in locations we don’t expect and in regions that defy our current understanding is an important reason why astronomers scan the heavens in search of other worlds</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/GenericGasGiant.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/GenericGasGiant.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The First Exoplanets: The Discovery That Forever Changed Us</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/the-first-exoplanets/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The First Exoplanets: The Discovery That Forever Changed Us" /><published>2023-08-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/discoveries/the-first-exoplanets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/discoveries/the-first-exoplanets/">&lt;div class=&quot;plyr&quot;&gt;

 Episode for August 7th, 2023
 &lt;audio id=&quot;player&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;https://archive.org/download/014-the-first-exoplanets-final/014_TheFirstExoplanets_final.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mp3&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/audio&gt;

 &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plyr.io/3.7.8/plyr.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
	  const player = new Plyr(&apos;#player&apos;, {
			    title: &quot;Example Title&quot;,
		    });
  &lt;/script&gt;  
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/download/014-the-first-exoplanets-final/014_TheFirstExoplanets_final.mp3&quot; class=&quot;btn btn--primary btn--large&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our galaxy likely holds hundreds of billions of planets around other stars but when and how did we begin finding them?  What was the first exoplanet detected?  It turns out that the first discovery wasn’t one, but two planets in the same system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The steady drumbeat of exoplanet discovery began in 1992 when astronomers Aleksander Wolszczan and Dale Frail found two rocky planets orbiting a type of neutron star known as a pulsar, a rapidly spinning stellar corpse that pulses with millisecond bursts of searing radiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measuring slight changes in the timing of the pulses is what allowed scientists to reveal the two rocky planets in orbit around the pulsar.The planets were named Poltergeist and Phobetor, and they were about the size of Earth and Neptune, respectively. They orbited the pulsar at distances of about where the asteroid belt and Uranus is in our solar system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These first two planets found by humans on Earth are not habitable. They are too close to the pulsar, and are constantly bombarded by radiation. However, their discovery showed that planets can exist around other stars, and it opened up the possibility that there may be habitable planets out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding these planets around this spinning star essentially opened the floodgates, and hinted that there must be planets everywhere because if we can find planets around a neutron star, which is a very harsh environment, then the planet production process must be very robust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little bit later astronomers started looking for planets like ours and the first planet detected around a Sun-like star was in 1995, and turned out to be a hot Jupiter: a gas giant about half the mass of our own Jupiter in an extremely close, four-day orbit around its star. A year on this planet, in other words, lasts only four days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From these exciting beginnings, over 5,000 exoplanets have since been discovered and some of them are located in the habitable zone of their stars, which is the region around a star where liquid water could exist on the surface of a planet. Some of these planets are even Earth-sized, which makes them even more likely to be habitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery of exoplanets has opened up a new chapter in our understanding of the universe. We now know that planets are not just a unique feature of our own solar system, but are common throughout the galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are on the cusp of a new era of discovery, and the possibilities are endless. We are on a quest that will hopefully answer some of the most fundamental questions about our place in the universe, and that could also change the course of human history.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tony Darnell</name><email>exoplanetradio@deepastronomy.com</email></author><category term="discoveries" /><summary type="html">The observations of planets around other stars is very recent and it changed our view of humanity&apos;s place in the universe forever.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/STScI-01GVGH2NDBHPT12FQPQA6AFZGC.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/STScI-01GVGH2NDBHPT12FQPQA6AFZGC.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>